<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Samaritan revived and the course he then took to cure the wounded traveller by powring in wine and oyl : historically applyed for the sound and speedy healing of our present dangerous distractions : with a sermon preacht by the same author upon Prov. 24:21 ... / by Matthew Griffith.</title>
            <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23761</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11213819</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204961</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240927047</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2016A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11213819</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1444:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Samaritan revived and the course he then took to cure the wounded traveller by powring in wine and oyl : historically applyed for the sound and speedy healing of our present dangerous distractions : with a sermon preacht by the same author upon Prov. 24:21 ... / by Matthew Griffith.</title>
                  <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665. Fear of God and the King.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Johnson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The sermon has special t.p.: The fear of God and the King (p. 51-110).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Fear of God --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Kings and rulers --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1660 --  Moral and ethical aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:1"/>
                  <p>THE SAMARITAN REVIVED: AND The course he then took to cure the wounded Traveller, by powring in Wine and Oyl.</p>
                  <p>Historically applyed for the sound and speedy Healing of our present dangerous Distractions.</p>
                  <p>With a Sermon preacht by the same AUTHOR upon</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PROV. 24.21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>My Son, fear God, and the King, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> MATTHEW GRIFFITH, <hi>D. D. and Chaplain to the late King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho: Johnson</hi> at the Golden Key in S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204961:2"/>
                  <head>The Samaritan revived.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a truth generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, That no state or condition on earth is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely perfect and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; so it hath been the unwearied en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of all that are wise and good, to attain unto happiness and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in every kind, as neer as humane frailty would admit. And because no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contributes more to happinesse then Government, which by curbing the unruly passions of men, doth both help to safeguard their persons, and distinguish their interests, so as they may freely and quietly enjoy what the Law calls their property; therefore the ancient Sages have taken a great deale of pains to find out, not onely what kind of Government is best in it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204961:3"/>selfe, but also what is most suitable and agreeable to the naturall complexion, and constitution of each particular Countrey, and accordingly our Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Ancestors (so renowned in Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their piety, prudence, courage, and loyalty) pitch'd at last upon Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, as not onely acknowledged on all hands to be the best forme of civill government, but as most proper to the humour, and most proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the temper of this ancient and formerly flourishing Nation.</p>
                  <p>And because they observed that the best things corrupted, do commonly prove worst, and that it is possible that Monarchy may degenerate into Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; therefore they provided that our Government (though Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) should be so contemper'd, that no Law should be imposed by the King upon the people, exacting their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, without their consent given by their Representatives assembled in Parliament (consisting of the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states) that as a threefold Cord is not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204961:3"/>easily broken: so if any of the three should become excentrick, the other two by their mutuall concurrence, and seasonable interposition, might evenly bound and ballance it. And we have felt of late by wofull experience, that when the House of Commons grew so praedominant, as first to vote down, and then quite take away the other two estates (which were of old more rightly, and more essentially interessed in the Legislative power then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and accordingly by assisting his Majesty should have restrain'd them) into what an <hi>Ilias</hi> of evils we have ever since been plung'd, and how sharply we have smarted for this their usurpation and intrusion.</p>
                  <p>And because what is said of that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that travailed between <hi>Jerusalem</hi> and <hi>Jericho,</hi> is too true of this Nation, which, to speak plainly, is fallen into the hands of Thieves, that have rob'd, and spoild it, and by so often wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, have now left it half dead, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how e're others of known abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204961:4"/>do account it good sleeping in a whole skin (passing by, like the Priest and the Levite branded in that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) and will take no cognizance of our lamentable case; least they should be ingag'd in, and either indamag'd or endanger'd by undertaking the cure; yet by Gods grace I am resolv'd (with the good <hi>Samaritan</hi>) to poure in both Wine and Oyle; that first by throughly searching the deep, if not deadly wounds of this Body politick with my Wine; and then gently suppleing it with my Oyle; I may do my utmost endeavour to heal and recover it.</p>
                  <p>And here, affecting brevity, I will pass by all such infirmities as a quick sight might have discern'd in the first ten years of the late Kings reign; and I will take my rise no farther then an ordinary Politician might have easily observ'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Kings of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and the States of the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, growing at that time dayly more and more potent by Sea and Land; and some of them not onely threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204961:4"/>invasion, but also year after year, and almost dayly committing upon the Narrow Seas, such out-rages and inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies as could not well be any longer endur'd: His Majesty (not only to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his own just greatness, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Nation, but also both to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Subjects at home, and to give check to the neighbouring Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; (all which without far greater supplies then the ancient revenue of the Crown, could not possibly then be done to any purpose) rais'd Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; yet not untill such time as divers of the Judges had freely deliver'd their Opinions, that in such Articles of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity he might lawfully do it. Now grant that the King had therein exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Praerogative a little too far (though when the case was argu'd, the Judges were divided about it, and one half of them stoutly &amp; stifly maintain'd it to be Law) yet in regard first he was in some sort then necessitated to do what he did, for the weighty reasons praealleadged; Next in regard it was all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204961:5"/>the taxe which was then yearly paid: To both which let me add, that in regard it was but a flea-bite to each particular man, in comparison of those insuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table pressures, under which we have laien groaning and gasping ever since; all sober and unbyassed men must, and will confesse, that it had been a great deal better for us to have pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endur'd that single inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then so many mischiefs as have since befallen us; and that had the Ship-mony been illegall, yet the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy hath been far worse then the Disease.</p>
                  <p>The ship-mony was no sooner assess<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but straight start up a disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted partie, which (having learn'd out of <hi>Machiavil,</hi> that it is best fishing in troubled waters) greedily laid hold upon that obliquitie, to render his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie odious: for they not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the payment, but fell downe right into seditious and tumultuous courses: for the effectuall composing whereof his Majestie thought that the speedy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204961:5"/>calling of a Parliament would be the most likely expedient; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly of his accustomed grace and clemencie, he issu'd out his writs to convene such a great Council as by their Wisdome and Moderation might wholly salve up what was past, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from all Innovations for the future. But the Tribunes of the People by ill Arts had so imbitter'd and exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the severall Counties and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, that instead of grave, able, and worthy Patriots, few or no Knights and Burgesses were chosen but of the old puritan Faction, whom this Church and State, ever since the Reformation, have found to be inveterate and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable Enemies to Peace and Truth; Both which though they seem'd to cry up in the Beginning of the late Troubles; yet it appeareth at this day that they will not lay down their Arms, that they may have Peace; nor yet leave their lying, that they may have Truth. These tender Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd Men (so they call'd themselves)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204961:6"/>had then an Opportunity put into their hands to actuate, what in Corners they had so many Ages together afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand design'd; <hi>viz.</hi> not onely the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Alteration, but utter Abolition and Extirpation of the so truly ancient and every way excellent Government both of Church and State; though the poor People that chose them, and many of them in the Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of their Souls, neither did, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed could give them any such unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and extravagant Power, as that Conventicle (being flesht with impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Successes) did afterwards by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees assume to Themselves; And I call it a Conventicle in the same Sence that the <hi>Trent</hi>-Council was so call'd, and because there was packing in Both much alike before the prevailing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in either could accomplish their Designs. The Members being met, after an hearty Thanksgiving among Themselves, that their Party was so numerous; and an hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Humiliation for the Evils they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204961:6"/>they fell close to work; and the better to carry on their Designs, they publisht a Remonstrance to the Kingdom, in which (with accursed <hi>Cham</hi>) they laid open their Civil Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers nakednesse (such as it was) and to render Him not onely odious, but ridiculous, they affix'd some personall faults upon Him, which He was in no wise guilty of. And his over-sights (if He had any) they did aggravate and embroider with such malicious Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, that they did thereby gull the well-meaning People into a kind of Credulity, or at least Anxiety; and so by little and little they did estrange and alienate their former good Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and dutifull Affections from their lawfull and gratious SOVERAIGN: a Practise treasonable in it self, and so confest to be in any others; yet, they not onely conniv'd at it in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and absolv'd themselves for it; but justified it as a Vertue both need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and commendable; which it is confest by their new Legislative Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204961:7"/>they might both as colourably and warrantably do, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the House of Peers did professedly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that we may do Evil that good may come thereof; and they had no other ground but his bare word (and that expresly contrary to Gods Word) whereon they built the whole Fabrick of their <hi>Ʋtopian</hi> Reformation: of which we can yet see no other Fruits but the Prophanation of Churches, yea, even of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> the renowned Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Church of this City and Nation, which is not onely turn'd into a Den of Thieves, but a Stable for Horses; which seem to have as much Religion and Christianity, as some of the Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beasts that ride them: and more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Oppressions by High Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, and other arbitrary Impositions, then ever were done by colour of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Reign of all the Kings since the Conquest. These and worse are the visible Fruits of their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Reformation, as you shall see ere I have done. The Foundation whereof
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204961:7"/>being laid in such rotten Principles, the Structure (though like the City-Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, it was somewhat specious at first, as being richly gilded, and fairly paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) was not likely to prove much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet they carryed on that which they call'd the Cause (for they were asham'd to call the Rebellion by its proper Name) vigorously, and brought it by Degrees to that goodly <hi>Babel,</hi> and confused Chaos that now it is: For first they contriv'd a Protestation, which (like a Viper) had its teeth so buryed in its gums, that it seem'd at first blush an harmless beast, though the bite thereof was deadly: for though the Protestation had divers plausible Pretences interwoven in it, and was made, as they said (like our ordinary Almanacks) onely for the Meridian of the House; yet as soon as the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers had taken it, it was impos'd upon the People; and the chief ends of it were; first, to cement the Factions fast each to other: Secondly, like a <hi>Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth</hi> to distinguish an Ephramite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204961:8"/>from an Israelite. Thirdly, to fortifie themselves against the King and all his Adherents; And fourthly, to bear them out against the Reach and Lash of all penall Laws, to which they might possibly become obnoxious in their future arbitrary Proceedings. And having thus prepar'd the Way, they fell to purging the House of all such as they call'd and counted ill-affected, and Malignants; that is, in plain English, they expell'd all such conscientious Persons, as either out of the Fear of GOD, or Fidelity to His Anointed, would not concur in their dangerous Votes, and detestable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions: and they purg'd it so often, and made their Potions so strong and fulsome, that ere long they had not left any considerable Number of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and upright Men among them. And the Purgative Physick having wrought as well as they could wish, the next thing they Voted was the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of some of his Majesties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest, and faithfullest Counsellors (as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204961:8"/>my Lord of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and others) whom they afterwards (as my Lord <hi>Digbie</hi> truly phras'd it) murther'd with the Sword of Justice: for my Lord of <hi>Strafford</hi> lost his Head onely for high Misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, as they call'd them; and the Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> suffer'd Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, onely to gratify the People of the Citie; which either out of Malice or Ignorance had petition'd that he should suffer for their Sins (it seems) for he was charg'd with none that were mortall; and the Diarie of his Life which they publish't to detract from his good Name, and Fame, shall keep both upon Record to sweeten his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall to all succeeding Generations. And when the Members had thus sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, if not shatter'd these two pillars, they caus'd others of His Majesties Friends in Order to Self-preservation to withdraw and conceale themselves seing that by their Stay, though they might have hazarded themselves, yet they could not have help'd Him who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204961:9"/>must no longer (forsooth) be trusted with the Militia (one of the fastest and fairest Flowers of the Crown, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which a monarch is a king and no King) but it must be put into suchhands as they could confide in: and that being taken away, A Vote or two stript Him of all Power, in a trice, both by Sea, and Land. All his Forts and Ports, Castles, Magazines and Ships, were not onely seiz'd by them; but both man'd, and kept, and turn'd, and fortified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Him. And about that Time Sir <hi>Richard Gournie</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> (a Man of so singular Integrity, that the whole City for the time stood upright in him) was committed to the Tower; and <hi>Isaack Penington</hi> substi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted; whose Name more properly should have been <hi>Iulian;</hi> For the Church of <hi>England</hi> never had so damn'd an Apostate, and firy a Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of her faithfull Sons, the loyall Clergy, as this <hi>Penington;</hi> during the time of whose Mayoralty most of the Orthodox Ministers were sequestred,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204961:9"/>and many of them clapt a Shipboard, and thrust into prisons, that their churches might be fill'd with such schismaticks and Sectaries, as would cry down the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> and bawl up the Cause;
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Till</hi> at Saint <hi>Olives</hi> in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> 1642.</note> and some of them came to such an heighth of Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, that they blusht not to preach to their amaz'd congregations, that this Parliament had done more good for us by their Reformation, then CHRIST had done by his passion. And as it is observ'd in the body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; that a raw stomack makes a rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick head, and a rheumatick head makes a raw stomack: So it proves no less true in the body politick, that a factious Church-man makes a sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Common-wealths-man; and a sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Common-wealths-man makes a factious Church-man: For the new Lay-Levites shewing the way, soon after, some of the members fell from whispering, to speak open Treason in the House: And when his <hi>Majesty</hi> in his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204961:10"/>own Person, attended with some few of his Meniall servants, required those five might be delivered up to a legall Triall, the House, (by the help of the City) not only protected the Traytors; but also Voted the <hi>Kings</hi> demand of them to be a high breach of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Parliament: and I believe, the <hi>Pope</hi> will as soon give us in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain List of Apostolicall Traditions, as the Parliament will do of their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; all which it is not held safe, for either Prince or People to know: These are <hi>Arcana imperii,</hi> and will help both <hi>Pope</hi> and Parliament out in all Exigences, and upon all Emergences whatsoever. The <hi>King</hi> being thus stript out of all power, and cheated out of the good affection of his liege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people; it was then but ask and have: The <hi>Kings</hi> Negative Voyce was voted down, and he now neither may, nor must deny the Members any thing. Then they Petition'd for a Triennial Parliament, and it was granted; yet that did not satisfie; for the truth is,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204961:10"/>they made use of the Trienniall, as a stalking horse to a perpetuall Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for which they had the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or rather the impudence, to petition too, though they knew that the <hi>King</hi> could not justly grant it, (as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the inevitable destruction of himself, and the people committed to his Trust;) yet they resolv'd, though the <hi>King</hi> could not grant it, yet he should not deny it: For while this hung in suspence, the Members tamper'd with <hi>Venne, Manwaring,</hi> and other Zelots (Citizens of desperate Opinions, and despicable fortunes) to sally with their <hi>Mirmydons</hi> down to <hi>White-hall</hi> in great numbers, &amp; greater disorder; whereas many Sea-men of the same strain were hyr'd under-hand to meet them by water; that so, what with their huge numbers, and their hideous noyse, they might at last intimidate the Court; and having thus first extorted from the <hi>King</hi> his consent to an Act for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Parliament, they might soon after induce, if not inforce him, by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204961:11"/>withdrawing himself from the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger of a popular fury, to provide, as well as possibly he could in such straits, for his present and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture preservation. The <hi>King</hi> being thus forc'd to absent himself, the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers laid about them lustily; passing Vote after Vote, and Order upon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; though I cannot stand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (neither is it much materiall if I could to say) either by what Artifice, or in what Order they passed them.</p>
                  <p>But to be short and plain; A new broad Seale was made; and by vertue thereof Commissions were issued forth to raise Forces by Sea and Land against the King, and his evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors (as they stil'd all that in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of their hearts did adhere unto him:) Open War was proclaim'd, &amp; the Zelots brought in to make that Calfe: Their plate, jewels, ear-rings, thimbles, and bodkins, which were first melted and then coin'd with the Parliaments stamp: Fears and Jealousies were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and fomented: new dangerous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204961:11"/>plots were daily discovered by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and contrivers of them: All known or suspected Loyallists were banisht out of the line of communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The companies of the City took their turns to march down to <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> daily to guard the House; and the Citie for the time seem'd to all sober men but a great Bedlam, in which, like so many mad men, they ratled with their chains, and hollowed, yea, and laughed, when in truth they did but help to hasten and lengthen their own misery. The <hi>Scots</hi> were call'd in to lend their brotherly assistance, and to this end a solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was equivocally pen'd, and taken; and impos'd as a snare, to entrap all conscientious Subjects: A Directory was publish't for Uniformity in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worship, which had neither the Lords Prayer, nor any of the three Creeds, nor the Decalogue in it: A Synod, or Assembly of Divines was chosen to do their jobs of Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work: The Bishops were first clapt in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204961:12"/>the Tower, and then voted downe root and branch, and so was the house of the Lords Temporall afterwards: A disgraceful Hue and Cry was sent after his Maiestie, and his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, and his no lesse innocent, then il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious Progeny were all stigmatiz'd: All that engag'd with, or but seem'd to favour Him, and his righteous Cause, were voted Delinquents, and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants: The Church of <hi>England</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any triall at all) was cast, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd: The observation of Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, yea of all the Feastivals kept in commemoration of Christ himself, was swep't away with an Ordinance: The Orthodox Clergy were sequestred: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge was justified to be no sin; and then the lands both of K. and Church were all sold: The Presbytery was set up for three years: Weekly Fasts and Humiliations then were continued from morning to night, which they us'd onely (as the Fryar spread his net) till they had caught the fish: Not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Popish, but Jesuitical positions were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204961:12"/>preach'd, press'd, and practised: as killing, yea, King-killing is no murther: Curse ye <hi>Meroz,</hi> then rung aloud in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pulpit. Tryers appointed to keep all right men out of the Church; and Committees authorized in all Cities and Counties, as an Inquisition to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise the faith and patience of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valliers. Great was the number of the Preachers; for a lying spirit made both some Lords, and their Coach-men; some Mechanicks, and their Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices; yea, some Mistresses and their Maid-maukins, all gifted in that kind; which were not able to discern and distinguish between faith and faction; reformation, and rebellion; consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and conspiracy; holiness and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrsie; yea, Jesuits disguis'd like seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral sorts of Handicrafts men in corners and Conventicles were encouraged to sow the seeds of Sedition and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilest the poor people were se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to follow them, &amp; to cry them up for gifted men, and so induc'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is no such need of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204961:13"/>preaching Ministers, since God in these reforming times has pour'd out his Spirit upon all flesh. And all men are taught of God both to pray and prophesie, if they would but stir up the grace that is in them, as these did who seem'd to have no other calling or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling then they themselves had. The schisme was dilated; Conventicles countenanc'd; The Scriptures maim'd and mangled, whilest they made use of the word of Christ, to betray the cause of Christ; divers Battails fought with various succes. Some Treaties pretēded by the House, but no accomodation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended; <hi>For he that draws his sword against his Prince, must cast away the scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> &amp;c. In fine, his <hi>Majesties</hi> forces were totally routed at <hi>Nazeby,</hi> and he being in a very great strait, put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into the hands of his native Countrey-men, the <hi>Scots;</hi> who trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherously sold him to the goodly Members sitting at <hi>Westminster,</hi> who after they had cag'd him a while, and hurried him from post to pillar (as we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204961:13"/>say) I mean from one prison and Jaylor to another; and finding that they held him like a Wolf by the ears; whether they held him, or let him go, they were still in danger; as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to satisfie and secure their own Guilt; they at last set up a mock-Court of Justice, in which they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally arraign'd and condemn'd him; and then most inhumanely murder'd him before the Gates of his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and usuall place of residence. <hi>Hic Finis</hi> CAROLI <hi>Fatorum,</hi> &amp;c. — And here observe by the way, that though the Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Anabaptists, and all other schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques and sectaries, may well be called <hi>LEGION,</hi> for they are many; yet though they be never so many, and never so far differing, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing each from other, in their heads; yet like <hi>Samsons</hi> Foxes, they are tyed together by the tayls: and like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> they agreed like bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in actuating this, which was as capitall a crime, and as horrid an ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204961:14"/>as ever the Sun beheld. And (which I may not pretermit in silence) when the Zelots first took up Arms, they pretended that they did it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>KING,</hi> but his evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellors: But God (who is the Tryer and Searcher of the Heart and the Reins) knew full well, that it was the <hi>Kings Person,</hi> &amp; <hi>Office</hi> that they rebel'd against; and therefore his Providence protected Him in the day of Battail, and put Him safe and sound into their hands: that all the World might see by their actuall murthering Him at last, that they had intentionally murther'd Him from the first rise of the Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Thus what they did with the full sway and swinge of their Wills, did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven against their Wills conduce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their making good in His <hi>Exit,</hi> what they had often promis'd in the Entrance of their damnable Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; <hi>viz.</hi> That they would make Him a <hi>Glorious King,</hi> meaning a <hi>King</hi> in <hi>GLORIE.</hi> To which let me add, that had the Sectaries been then sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204961:14"/>they would then have ever hanckered after Rebellion, and cryed what glorious things they would have done, had they prospered in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformation. And therefore Divine Providence so ordered the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse, that the worse Cause for the time got the better, to stop their Mouths, and let them see that their so <hi>head-strong</hi> and <hi>brain-sicke Ʋndertakings</hi> (though seemingly prosperous for a time) tended only to, and ended only in their own Confusion.</p>
                  <p>The King being thus translated, and all His Royal Progeny being banish'd for the present, and by an Act of this perpetuall Parliament, for ever disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled from swaying the three Scepters of their Birthright; and the Kingdoms themselves being strangely metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos'd into a Common-wealth, as some are pleas'd to call it (The
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>The name of the beast,</hi> 666.</note> pUbLIke WeaLth of engLanD) though all the naturall Subjects, and free-born Inhabitants, finde it in Truth to be a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204961:15"/>Common, or Publique Woe; for all things are now so farre out of course, that we can neither well indure the Disease nor the Remedie; and so it seems to fare with us at this day, as once it did with <hi>GODS</hi> own people, of whom it is said, <hi>That when there was no King in Israel, every one did that which seemed right in his owne Eyes;</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, few, or none did that then which was right in <hi>GODS</hi> eyes. And this being just our Case in this <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum;</hi> The Factions that were so combin'd in prosecuting, and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the King, began to fall asunder in dividing the Spoil, and each set up for it selfe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> as they had the largest share in the Plunder at first (and so were best able to purchase the Lands lately belonging to the King and the Church) so had they then the greatest power; for the Generall, and the Admirall, <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Warwicke</hi> were both theirs. But after <hi>Essex</hi> his death
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204961:15"/>(whether it were naturall, as some say he dyed of a Surfet, he being a noted Epicure that serv'd no other God, but his own belly; or as others say, it was violent, and that he was poyson'd; which if true, was the just Reward of his Rebellion) the morally Jacobite <hi>Independents</hi> out-witted their Brethren, and their <hi>Elders</hi> too, I mean the <hi>Esau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite Presbyterians,</hi> and got for a time both the <hi>Birthright,</hi> and the <hi>Blessing</hi> of the Civill Power, and conduct of the Armie into their hands, till e're long the Lieutenant General <hi>O. Cromwell</hi> (a man fast to no Religion, but Interest) by his <hi>Absalom</hi>-like Insinuation with the Commanders, and by his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praying, and other Gifts in cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, had so gain'd the generall good Opinion of the Common Souldiers, that he was on the sodain proclaim'd <hi>Protector:</hi> And though all men look'd upon him as a meer Usurper, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder; Yet he did so shuffle and pack the Cards (sometimes making <hi>Friends,</hi> otherwhiles preventing <hi>Enemies</hi>) that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204961:16"/>what between Love and Feare, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Punishments, he held rast what he had so unjustly seiz'd on, so long as he lived; And if any wonder how he first got, and then held the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Dignity? Let me tell them, that this brave <hi>Oliver,</hi> besides that he was a Gentleman born, and so had liberall Education at Home in Peace, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the Wars; he was also a man of excellent naturall Parts, and so tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a Politician, that he check'd at nothing which was ill: He paved his way to Preferment, through Blood, Perjury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And having got the Power, he laid aside the golden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as an insignificant bauble for legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Princes to play with, and please themselves; and rul'd this (which he observ'd to be a stirring, and a head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong people) with a <hi>Rod of Iron:</hi> If, with <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, he met with such a <hi>Gordian knot,</hi> as he could not well untie, he strait cut it in two with his sword: And when the pummel was too blunt, then (with <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204961:16"/>he turn'd the Point, which he kept sharp, and speedy in the Execution of Justice, be it right or wrong, as we say: And though our former <hi>Princes</hi> look'd upon <hi>Parliaments</hi> with some dread; and both King and people have of late smarted under them: Yet this <hi>Oliver</hi> call'd, and broke them up when he pleas'd. He plaid with <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as Ladies do with Serpents without stings, and made their power fruitless, their Malice toothlesse. Briefly, he made <hi>Spain, France,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> for the Time like the Sect we call <hi>Quakers,</hi> and to stand in fear of Him, whom they did not, could not love.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the eldest son of <hi>Oliver</hi> was (as <hi>Thurloe</hi> said) design'd to succeed his Father in the <hi>Protectorship;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly declar'd by the then Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>State:</hi> and his second son <hi>Henry</hi> continued a while his Vicegerency in <hi>Ireland;</hi> but the Members of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Parliament (having an aking tooth against <hi>Oliver,</hi> for expelling them the House, and taking them from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204961:17"/>Receipt of Custome (which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but a customary Deceit, feeding themselves fat by starving of us, and filling their own purses by emptying, and exhausting ours) observing the said <hi>Richard</hi> &amp; <hi>Henry,</hi> for want either of Reason or Resolution, to be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit to rule; and taking advant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of their manifold wants and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, I say, the said Members then (being countenanced by some of the chief Officers of the Army) re-entred the House, as their ancient Inheritance and Free-hold: and between Hopes and Feares prevailed with those two Novices, to quit their places and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without any Bustle, or visible Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; And the two tame Creatures being gone, the beasts of Prey (which had been so long kept fasting) grew the more keen and ravenous, swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all they could seize upon, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glution: But the poor Members were much deceived in looking for an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Citie here, and to sit down &amp; rest; for e're they were wel vvarm'd in their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204961:17"/>Seats Lieut. Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> (a Prince of <hi>Oliver's</hi> Faith, who had learn't of his great Lord and Master, to keep no Oaths, or Engagements, Covenants, Vowes, or Promises, but what he wanted either Opportunity, or Power to break) routed them again, and put them on the sodain to seek out new Habitations. And the nine dayes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was hardly over, ere <hi>Lambert</hi> and his Confederates found that their Head-pieces were sounder and better then their Heads; and that they had made a great deal more haste, then good speed: for upon mature delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they could not but be sensible, that the common Souldiers were then ready to mutiny for want of pay; and that the Officers, had neither ready monies to stop their mouths; nor any possible way whereby to raise them. Besides the Day of our Redemption drawing near; and the people being wearied, if not worried, by such chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings and changings, as they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd in Church, and State, (which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204961:18"/>had run through all Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without any present satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or hopes of future settlement) and that after so prodigal an effusion of Time, Treasure, and Bloud, they had done in effect nothing all this while, but undone themselves: then as (if GOD had put a new Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the old <hi>Britains,</hi> which had opened their eyes) it seemes that all Counties, and Corporations, and this City above the rest, had, underhand promis'd to rise as one man; and to stand for a free Parliament, (which they knew could not legally be called without the King) as the onely visible meanes to redeem us, and our Posterity, from the House of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; in which we have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd so many years to make the full tale of Bricks, though our hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Taskmasters would not allow us the usual proportion of straw. But however this Animosity, and underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king was concluded on to be univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall throughout the Kingdom; yet the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204961:18"/>rest being prevented, and for the time disappointed, Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and his party in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> were the first, if not the onely men, (beside Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton,</hi> with some few of the <hi>Welsh</hi>) that took the Field in a considerable Body: The Report whereof had no sooner alarm'd these <hi>Southern</hi> parts, but a Council of Warre was call'd; and <hi>Lambert</hi> was appointed to march <hi>North-west,</hi> to quell the Rebels (as they called them) yet he did not set for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward till such time as the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and (their spawn) the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and all other Sectaries were put into Arms here; as the onely godly party, in which, both the Army, and <hi>Ireton</hi> (then Lord Mayor) and <hi>Titchborn,</hi> with some other prime Citizens of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, could then confide. And Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Fleetwood</hi> undertaking to keep all quiet here, his Lieutenant General (with such Forces as could well be spared) did advance towards <hi>Cheshire:</hi> whose expectation being foil'd by the not timely rising of the Associated
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204961:19"/>Counties; the <hi>Cheshire-men</hi> were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd without any great dispute; and <hi>Lambert,</hi> without a blow, had soon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd victorious; but that foul-wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the <hi>North</hi> compell'd him to make an halt, and to put on new resolutions: for that Generall <hi>Monk</hi> had taken the Field, and was marching <hi>Southward;</hi> though whether as a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, or as invited by the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians hither; it is not yet discovered. While <hi>Lambert</hi> was absent, he dispatcht severall Missives to <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> as so many Cautions, to keep the Members from re-admission into the House; which though he Religiously observ'd, as far as he was able, yet <hi>Hazlerigge, Morley,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Rump,</hi> (for so they were abusively then call'd between the scorn and hatred of the common people) outwitting and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the phlegmatique Generall, did by such power as they brought with them from <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> force their re-entry into the House; and did, Spider-like, eviserate and spin out
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204961:19"/>themselves, and their time, that so they might not want new Cobwebs (such as the Oath of Abjuration, and the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessment of an hundred thousand pounds a Moneth, and such like trifles) wherein to entangle and engage us. As the House sate, hatching these Cocatrice Eggs, they cast <hi>Lambert</hi> such a bone to pick, as beat out all his teeth, and left him no more power, then ordinarily the prince of this world gives to the children of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, whom he strips and whips at last, as the Guerdon of their former service: and <hi>Lamberts</hi> forces being dispers'd by an Order of the House, Generall <hi>Monk</hi> marched on hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards without the least opposition; and which is more, all the Counties which lay in, or neer the way, as he march'd, did unanimously petition him (as if he had been some petty Prince, and Saviour of the people, as we hope he will prove, ere he hath done) for a free Parliament; promising withall, that in order thereunto, they would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204961:20"/>stand to him with their lives and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; but both his carriage and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, were then so reserv'd and doubtfull, that the Petitioners were dismissed with little satisfaction, save that the man is eminently civil. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which Petitioners, there were divers honest men, both of the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Common Council, and young men of the City; who (for shewing their good affections to such a free Parliament) were secur'd in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and other prisons: for though the Members used to give thanks to such as presented them with Petitions, fram'd in the House, and subscrib'd both in City and Countrey, according to their direction (which decoy was grown stale, and almost out of fashion) yet now, when they saw all parts peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a free Parliament, (which they resented as destructive to their new model'd <hi>Common-wealth</hi>) they grew more impatient, and insolent, then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary; especially when upon Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Monks</hi> first approach, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204961:20"/>his fair compliance, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward observance of the Councill of States extravagant Order; To break down the City gates, and to pull up their posts, and chains, a violence so unexpected, that it did not onely star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the honest Common-Council for the present; but it so extreamly disgu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the Citizens in generall, that though soon after he laboured to salve up the matter by some healing plaist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; yet they did not forget, that he had not onely broke their heads, but had with some dishonour made them, for the time, to pull in their Horns; with which they had (like so many mad Oxen) gored the King and his party during the continuance of the War; which as it took its first rise thence, so God grant it may not end there, as the just punishment of their factious forwardnesse.</p>
                  <p>To sweeten them again, he scatter'd a few sugar-plums among them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising that they should have a <hi>Free Parliament:</hi> and thereupon the giddy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204961:21"/>multitude straight made great acclamations, some of them openly in the streets, crying <hi>God blesse King</hi> CHARLES, God send us a King again; and others drank healths to the King and to the General, as they were then well warm'd with strong drink, as well as with the flame of the Bonfires: And you will easily believe, that all the Bels in <hi>London</hi> rung for joy; though the more grave and sober sort saw not then any great reason why: Yea to this day, the Rump is so far from being routed, that they are rather recruited: and so onely inabled to do more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, unlesse many of the secluded Members (which are lately introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) are become Real Converts (as it is not without some good grounds ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally hop'd) though for the present, the Qualifications w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> they prescribe to all <hi>Counties</hi> and <hi>Corporations</hi> to be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly observ'd in the Election of the new <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgesses,</hi> give the whole Kingdome just cause to suspect, that the intent and meaning of the House,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204961:21"/>is to have no free choise at all, because they will not allow any to be chosen as Members of the next, but onely such as have signally testified their good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to this: and (if I may deliver my mind without offence) I cannot see (as things now stand) how they can le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally issue out Writs to call a new Parl. without the Kings consent; Or grant they could, why the Members now as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, should not have altogether as much power and will to redeem their poor bleeding Countrey vvhich they have thus imbroil'd, as the next can have, supposing it to be as good as possibly can be chosen.</p>
                  <p>Thus with the good <hi>Samaritans</hi> wine, I have search'd the yet festering sores of the <hi>Body-Politicke;</hi> I have lanc'd them to the quick, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let out the impostumated matter, but taken away the proud, and dead flesh; for God knows that it is the humble, and earnest desire of my heart and soul rather soundly to heale our wounds, then onely superficially to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204961:22"/>skin them over; lest if they break out again, the parts that are ill-affected, should gangrene, and so the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perish. Now I come with the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan</hi> to pour in my Oyl, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply an healing <hi>Balsam;</hi> to which do you joyn with me in prayer, that God would be pleas'd to give his blessing.</p>
                  <p>The most authentique Physitians say, that the exact knowledge of any Disease, is the first step to the Cure: and that the next is a velliety in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to be made whole: The former (by Gods assistance) we have attain'd unto by that discovery, which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been made; and that the latter is no lesse necessary, may be gather'd from that unexpected question, which our blessed Lord himself started to the man that had layn so many years cripl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Pool of <hi>Bethesda; Wilt thou be made whole?</hi> which had been super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacaneous, but that some will not; as the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> speaks of <hi>Babylon; We would have cured Babylon, but she would not be healed.</hi> And Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moans
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204961:22"/>
                     <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> saying, <hi>How often would I have gathered thee, even as an hen gathers her chickens under her wings? But thou wouldst not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus at this day we see some of our ordinary beggars go about with scal'd heads, and running sores upon them; who might be cured in our Hospitals, and cost them nothing; yet they will not; partly, that they may have the more plausible cause to beg, and partly that they may beget more compassion in the spectators; but principally, that these visible griefs may be a supersede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as against the Statute, that provides such Vagrants should be set in the stocks, or sent to the House of Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And the truth is, that there be divers members at this day, both of Church, and State, that will by no meanes endure to hear of any healing <hi>Balsam,</hi> or so much as the least over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Accomodation; because they are afraid, that if the times should turn, and the Law (which is the rule of Right) should take place; they should
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204961:23"/>then not only lose the sweet liberty, or rather licenciousnesse, to say, and do what they list, but also be constrained to refund by Restitution, and vomit up e're long all such goods, or lands, as they have (against law and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) already swallowed.</p>
                  <p>And to such particular cases (of which there is no end) it is impossible for any man to apply so many proper Remedies: All such must be relieved by some special Act of <hi>Parl.</hi> provided, when there is cause: My scope is to heal the body Politick, and so many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof (as being become truly sensible of the mortal disease in which they have so long lain languishing) are willing to be restor'd to their former health and happinesse; as the three na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (formerly sway'd by one graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monarch) do jointly and severally now profess themselves to be.</p>
                  <p>And as our first distemper grew into a form'd disease, and that pestilential, because when things were out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we did not humble our selves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204961:23"/>God in prayer, quickned with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting (prayers and teares being all the weapons that God allows Christians to take up against their lawfull Princes) but made our addresses onely to a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> in which alone we did then put all our belief, and confidence: so God hath now severely scourg'd us with that arm of flesh, which as an Idol we set up in his stead (and so we can justly blame none but our selves, for we reap but what we sow'd, and drink but what we brew'd) and he hath turn'd that which we look'd upon as our onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, into an Epidemical, and almost incurable maladie; to bring us at last to acknowledge ingeniously, that as neither power nor policy can prevail against Gods institution: so we must depend upon him alone for safety, and salvation. King <hi>Asa</hi> was onely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a disease in his feet (one would think it was far enough from his heart) and yet because he sought to the Physician for help in the first place, when as he should have gon unto God,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204961:24"/>it proved mortal. And as the woman of <hi>Syro-phaenecia,</hi> that so many years was troubled with <hi>an issue of blood,</hi> though she spent all she had upon Physicians, yet was not cured till she came to Christ: So howe're it must be confess'd, that a <hi>Parliament</hi> rightly constituted, be a proper Physician for the <hi>Body-Politick,</hi> yet it cannot cure our present <hi>Bloody-flux,</hi> without the special concurrence and benediction of the Almighty; for it is most certain that no second Cause can work to any purpose, without the influence, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of the first.</p>
                  <p>The Law both of God, and this Land, run all upon the right, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Kings,</hi> under whom (as Gods Ordinance) we have not onely liv'd, but flourished many hundred yeares: All the free-born people of these three Kingdoms, are bound not only by the former oaths of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;</hi> but also by the <hi>Protestation,</hi> and the <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all means the preservation
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:204961:24"/>of the <hi>King,</hi> and his Successors, and consequently of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, who is the undoubted Heir of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers rights, and our hopes; without whose gracious concurrence no Law can be binding to us, and during whose exile, we have lived onely under <hi>Ʋsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> enmity and animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, poverty for want of trade, and continual excessive assessments to pay the Souldiers, who can never have all their arrears before we have a <hi>King:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we expect to see any end of War and Blood-shed, and all the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and miseries which now lie so heavy upon us, till our lawful King be reduc'd and restor'd. As when a bone is broken, or out of joynt, the Patient can never be freed from exquisit pain, till it be not onely set, but set right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: so though we have been long not onely out of joynt, but even bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces; and have suffered inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressible pangs and pains; yet to this day we feel little or no ease, because none have had us in hand, but such
<pb facs="tcp:204961:25"/>
                     <hi>Empericks</hi> and <hi>Mountehancks,</hi> as (want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either skill or fidelity) have in stead of healing our wounds, inflam'd the distemper. None can set us right again, but only He, who is (under God) our proper <hi>Physitian,</hi> and Father of our Countrey. Then a <hi>King</hi> we must have, for none can extricate us out of all those difficulties and dangers in which we have so deeply involved our selves; none can give just and full sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to all Factions and interests, but a <hi>King.</hi> And He, not a <hi>Perkin Warbek,</hi> nor yet a baffled <hi>Richard,</hi> but our lawfull <hi>King,</hi> CHARLES; without whom we are now convinc'd, that we can neither enjoy our birth-right in this world, nor Gods blessing in the world to come; notwithstanding all the former or later blasphemies of our <hi>Rabshekehs:</hi> After that <hi>Saul</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed <hi>King,</hi> he was despised by some, as we read in the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Chapter of the first Book of <hi>Samuel:</hi> but it is to be noted, that God there calls those that despised the <hi>King,</hi> sons of <hi>Belial;</hi> (as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:204961:25"/>having cast off the yoke, for so the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word signifies.) Now you know it was the Devil who first cast off Gods yoke, when affecting equality, he said, <hi>I will be like the most High.</hi> And they are call'd the sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> that did then and there cast off the <hi>Kings</hi> yoke: but those that cast off the yoke of God, and the <hi>King;</hi> and of God in the <hi>King;</hi> (yea, though it were but king <hi>Saul</hi>) were themselves but so many cast aways; for they were of their father the Devil, saith our Saviour; there's their Pedigree. But the Text I quoted out of <hi>Samuel,</hi> adds withall, <hi>that the band of men of chivalry, whose hearts God had touch'd, follow'd king</hi> Saul <hi>home to</hi> Gibeah; whence I necessarily infer, that those which in this generall desire and endeavour fairly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose things in difference, do not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God and the King, shew plainly, that God hath not yet touch'd their hearts; which as soon as he hath done effectually, they will be brought to confess, that without the restitution of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204961:26"/>
                     <hi>King</hi> CHARLES to his native rights, we can in reason look for no solid settlement of Religion, or Law, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or Propertie, Peace or plenty, honour or safety. To all these we can never be firmly restor'd but by the <hi>King;</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> not forc'd to come by his birth-right as a Conqueror, but fairly call'd in, either by this or the next Parliament: That as our sins in choosing heretofore, and hitherto cleaving to a factious Parliament, have almost utterly ruin'd us, so this, or a free Parliament (upon their and our serious repentance) may be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall (under God) to make us speedy reparation.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:27"/>
                  <p>THE FEAR OF GOD AND THE KING. Press'd in a Sermon, Preach'd at MERCERS Chappell, on the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>MARCH,</hi> 1660.</p>
                  <p>TOGETHER WITH <hi>A brief Historical account of the Causes of our unhappy Distractions, and the onely way to Heal them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> MATTHEW GRIFFITH, <hi>D. D. and Chaplain to the late King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho: Johnson</hi> at the Golden Key in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1660.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:28"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:28"/>
                  <head>TO HIS EXCELLENCY, George Monck, CAPTAIN GENERAL of all the land forces of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> And one of the <hi>Generals</hi> of all the Naval-forces.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you will be pleased to allow me to be a <hi>Physitian</hi> in the same sense that all Morall <hi>Divines</hi> do acknowledge the Body-Politick (consisting both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi>) to be a <hi>Patient,</hi> then I will now give your <hi>Highness</hi> a just account, both how far, and how faithfully I have practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed upon it, by vertue of my <hi>Profession.</hi> When I first observed things to be somewhat out of order, by reason of a light <hi>distemper,</hi> which then appeared by some infallible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications;
<pb facs="tcp:204961:29"/>I thought it my duty, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe an wholsome <hi>Electuary,</hi> (out of the <hi>122. Psalm,</hi> at the 6. verse, in a <hi>Sermon</hi> which I was called to Preach in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church of Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> Anno, <hi>1642.</hi> and I soon after publish't by command, ander this Title, <hi>A Patheticall Perswasion to pray for the publique peace)</hi> to be duly and devoutly taken every morning next our hearts; hoping that by Gods blessing on the <hi>Means,</hi> I should have prevented that <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemper</hi> from growing into a form'd dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease; yet finding that my preventing <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick</hi> did not work so kindly, and take so good an effect as I earnestly desired; but rather that this my so tenderly beloved <hi>Patient</hi> grew worse and worse; as not only being in process of time fallen into a <hi>feaver,</hi> and that <hi>pestilentiall,</hi> but also as having received divers dangerous wounds, which <hi>ranckling</hi> and <hi>festring</hi> inwardly, brought it into a spirituall <hi>Atrophie,</hi> and deep <hi>Consumption;</hi> and the parts ill-affected (for want of <hi>Christian</hi> care, and skill in such <hi>Mountebancks</hi> as were trusted with the cure, while my self, and most of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:204961:29"/>
                     <hi>Orthodox Clergie</hi> were sequestred and silenc'd) began to gangrene: and when some of us became sensible therof, we took the confidence, (being partly embolden'd by the connivence of the <hi>higher Powers</hi> that then were) to fall to the exercise of our Ministeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Function</hi> again, in such poor <hi>Parishes</hi> as would admit us: then I saw that it was high time, not onely to prescribe strong pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative medicines in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> (contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered of the Myrrhe of <hi>Mortification;</hi> the Aloes of <hi>Confession,</hi> and <hi>Contrition;</hi> the Rubarb of <hi>Restitution</hi> and <hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> with divers other safe roots, seeds and flowers, fit and necessary to help to carry away by degrees, the incredible confluence of ill humours, and all such malignant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as offended) but also, to put Pen to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and to appear in <hi>Print</hi> (as in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and impolish'd piece, which as guilty of an high presumption, here in all humility begs your <hi>Lordships Pardon</hi>) wherein my chief scope is to personate the good <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan;</hi> that as he cur'd the wounded <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller,</hi> by searching his wounds with <hi>wine,</hi> and suppleing them with <hi>oyle:</hi> so I have
<pb facs="tcp:204961:30"/>here, both described the <hi>Rise,</hi> and <hi>Progress</hi> of our nationall malady, and also prescrib'd the onely Remedy; that I might be in some kind instrumentall under <hi>God</hi> and your <hi>Highness,</hi> in the healing of the same.</p>
                  <p>And for both my present undertaking, and dedication, St. <hi>Luke</hi> (Chap. <hi>1.3.</hi>) makes an Apologie; <hi>It seem'd good unto me, having had perfect understanding of things from the very first, to write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in order (most excellent</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus) <hi>that thou might'st know the certainty of those things wherein thou hast been instructed.</hi> And because we are now upon the point of recovery, and there is little visible cause of danger, save onely by relapsing: therefore in a Sermon (which I was very lately cal'd to preach at <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel) I have prescrib'd an wholsome dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et (approv'd of in <hi>Prov. 24.21.</hi>) &amp; which I have here also publish'd; and I make no question but if it be conscientiously observ'd, it will serve to prevent all relapsing in this kind for the future. Yet because Gods word is never more lively and mighty in operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then when it is countenanc'd, and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
<pb facs="tcp:204961:30"/>with the power of the Sword; give me leave not onely to crave your Lordships pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage to this poor <hi>Vade-mecum;</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so your gracious concurrence, &amp; couragious carrying on of what you have already so happily begun in the name and cause of God, and his Anointed, till you have finish'd this great, and good work, and brought it to perfection: That we, and our children (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom your name will be for ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious) may truly say of you, as the Roman Histories do of <hi>Fabritius, The Sun may sooner be brought to alter his course, then you to alter your most heroick Resolution.</hi> My Lord, as it must needs grieve you to see these three distressed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms lye, like a Body without a Head: so it may also chear you to consider that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter hath impowr'd you, (and in this nicke of time, you onely) to make these dead and dry bones, live; You may by this one Act ennoble and aeternize your selfe more in the hearts and chronicles of these three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; then by all your former Victories, and the long line of your extraction from the <hi>Plantagenets,</hi> your Ancestors, which gave
<pb facs="tcp:204961:31"/>
                     <hi>names to the Kings of</hi> England for many generations. It is a greater honour to make a <hi>King,</hi> then to be one. Your proper name minds you of being St. <hi>George</hi> for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> your Sirname prompts you to stand for order: then let not panicke fears, puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio's of humane policy, or State-formalities, beguile you (whom we look upon as <hi>Jethro's</hi> Magistrate, who was a man of courage, fearing God, dealing truly, and hating co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousness) of that immarcescible Crown of Glory due to you, whom we hope that God hath design'd to be the repairer of the breach, and the temporall Redeemer of your native Countrey. The case of <hi>Rome</hi> differs so much from our present condition; that what prudent <hi>Fabius</hi> restor'd by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, you cannot now possibly compasse without expedition. All our hopes (under God) depend upon your skill at the Helme. Give me leave to conclude (as <hi>Mordecai</hi> clos'd with <hi>Ester (4.13.—) Think not with thy selfe that thou shalt escape in the Kings house, more then the rest: for if thou forbearest at this time, then shall our enlargement and deliverance
<pb facs="tcp:204961:31"/>rise from some other place; but thou, and thy house shall be destroyed: And who knows whether God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd thee for such a time as this?</hi> Thanke God for the power and opportunity you have now in your hands; and pardon the seasonable application by Him; who (as he is too old to fear, and too great a sufferer to flatter) hath no other ambition, but to deliver his own soul, and the Nation, by sincerely approving himself</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The humblest of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships servants, and truest honourers,</hi> MAT: GRIFFITH.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:32"/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:204961:32"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PROV. 24.21.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>My son, feare God, and the King, and meddle not with them that be seditious, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of change, &amp;c.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, and the King, at the first blush, seem to stand in the Text, like those two <hi>Cherubims</hi> on the <hi>Mercy-seat (Exod. 37.9.) looking on each other:</hi> yet with this difference, That God is an heavenly King, and eternal, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. but the King is an earthly, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, <hi>Psal.</hi> 82.6.—And yet in a qualified sence, they are both <hi>Gods,</hi> and both <hi>Kings,</hi> and therefore both to be feared, as you are exhorted in the Text; <hi>My son, feare God, and the King, and meddle not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:204961:33"/>
                  <p>In which words (for my more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly proceeding, and your better profiting) be pleas'd to observe with me these four principall parts, <hi>viz.</hi> A Preacher, and his Auditory; His Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and his Use.</p>
                  <p>The first, <hi>viz.</hi> This Preacher is a Prince too; and in both a transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
                  <p>The second, <hi>viz.</hi> His Auditory, are Sons; and therefore reverent, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient.</p>
                  <p>The third, <hi>viz.</hi> His Doctrine is, <hi>Feare God, and the king;</hi> a Doctrine at all times most expedient.</p>
                  <p>The 4<seg rend="sup">th.</seg>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> His Use is, <hi>Medle not with them that be seditious, or desirous of change:</hi> An Use at this time not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. And therefore—</p>
                  <q>My son, feare God, and the King, and medle not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>This Preacher, <hi>Solomon,</hi> and his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, <hi>Sons;</hi> I will touch onely (as a <hi>Praeface</hi> to my ensuing discourse) in a word or two; for no <hi>Praeface</hi> should be long.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:204961:33"/>
                  <p>We find upon record (in the 16. chapter of St. <hi>Luke</hi>) that Rich man su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Father <hi>Abraham, sub forma pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris,</hi> that one might be sent from the dead to preach to his five surviving brethren: And though his Petition was denied upon an aequitable reason, yet it seems here to be granted: For if there be any Vertue more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in the Sermons of the dead, I hope there will now some good be wrought on, and in you; for here is one that preaches to you from the dead; and this <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> was a <hi>Non si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut;</hi> for whilest he liv'd, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed on all sides to be the wisest <hi>Preacher,</hi> and the wealthiest <hi>Prince</hi> that ever spake out of a Pulpet, or swai'd a Scepter: and he that is both wise, and wealthy, can never want an Auditory: It is King <hi>Solomon</hi> that preaches here; I am but his Eccho; the plain song is His; mine's but the descant; the Text is His, mine's but the Paraphrase, Glosse, or Commentarie: yea, should I repeat but onely his Text once more,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204961:34"/>you must acknowledge it to be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Sermon, and a seasonable one too: and God grant it may work kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon you at this time, as it hath in the worst of times done on me, I thank the grace of God for it; and here I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and ingenuously profess for my own part, that I never heard a better Sermon then this which wise <hi>Solomon</hi> preaches and presses here, <hi>My son, fear God, and the king, and meddle not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And as the Sermon is his, so I trust I may truly say that his Auditory is mine: for though men were never of more different perswasions in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Nation, then they have been of late; yet such is my christian charity, that there is not any one person in this great Assembly, to whom in truth and tendernesse of my particular affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as in King <hi>Solomons</hi> genuine acception of the tearm, I may not say, <hi>My son:</hi> For (as the learned observe) the son he speaks to here was not his son by natural generation (as the term is ordinarily used elsewhere) but only
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204961:34"/>by paternall good affection: and so you are all my <hi>Sonnes;</hi> and so you shall be, not only whether you will, or no, but also whether I will, or not: for long since have I bound my self to you (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> speaks, <hi>ad Abbatem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstratensem</hi>) in holy charity, even that love which never fails; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no miscariage of yours can make me cancell this <hi>bond of perfectnesse</hi> (as the Apostle dignifies it) but as an old (though unworthy) Minister of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel of Christ I must own, and call each of you, <hi>my son.</hi> Thoug some <hi>Interpreters</hi> (I must tel you) make no more of this loving compellation, then that <hi>Solomon</hi> (being an exact Preacher) useth here, what <hi>Rhetoricians</hi> call <hi>Captatio benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiae;</hi> and so he saith, <hi>my sonne,</hi> when he would gently perswade his Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to feare <hi>God, and the King:</hi> As if he had said <hi>(as it was his full intent and meaning)</hi> He that <hi>fears God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> as he should and ought, shall no longer be my subject or servant onely, but he shall be henceforward my son,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:204961:35"/>by my gracious acceptation, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption: And you all know well that it is no mean honour to be the reputed sonne of such a King, as King <hi>Solomon;</hi> or rather of a greater, better King then he, even of God himself, <hi>whose sons you are, if you fear him,</hi> as he exhorts in the Text: <hi>And not only his sons</hi> (saith S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 8. to the <hi>Romans</hi>) <hi>but heires too: Heires of God, and joynt heirs with Christ;</hi> and that of no lesse then two incomparable Kingdoms, <hi>viz: The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace in this life, and the kingdome of glory in the life to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hitherto, of the Preacher, <hi>Solomon;</hi> and his Auditory, <hi>Sons;</hi> which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they deserve to be amplified, and embroider'd with variety of the most orient colours, yet I have purpose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forborn, because I told you that for this once, I would use them onely as <hi>Praeface;</hi> and I hope you will the rather pardon me, because by this means I am enabled to make the more hast to the Doctrine of the Text, <hi>Feare God, and the king:</hi> which is a doctrine at all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204961:35"/>times most expedient: and herein let me again commend to your christian observation, both a single Act, Feare, and a double Object, <hi>God, and the king.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And because these three terms, <hi>Fear, God, King,</hi> are better understood in the Theory, as notions; then observed in our practice, and conscientiously o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd; therefore in stead of spending so precious time in opening the terms, and of telling you what you know well enough already; I shall onely intreat you to take speciall notice of two things therein, which I believe to be most materiall:</p>
                  <p>One is, the conjunction and combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of these terms; for it is not, <hi>Feare God</hi> alone; or <hi>fear</hi> only <hi>the King:</hi> but it is, <hi>Fear God, and the King,</hi> both together.</p>
                  <p>The other is, the right order and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of them; for it is said here, first <hi>fear God;</hi> and then <hi>fear the king, My Son, fear,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And now, If in the first place we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave regard to the conjunction of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204961:36"/>these terms, we cannot but observe, that <hi>God and the king</hi> are coupled in the Text; and what the Holy Ghost hath thus firmly combin'd, we may not, we must not dare to put asunder: for in the seventh Chapter of <hi>Judges,</hi> at the 20. verse, The sword of the Lord and <hi>Gideon,</hi> is spoken of as but one two-handed sword; the Lord gives it, and <hi>Gideon</hi> girds it to himself <hi>Gideon</hi> gives the blow, &amp; the Lord gives the blessing; and Kings at their <hi>Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> have a sword given them; the <hi>Militia;</hi> the power of life and death is put into their hands; for the King is Gods Sword-bearer, and he <hi>bears not the sword in vain,</hi> saith the Apostle Rom. 13.4. And therefore he bear it not in vain, because God hath put it into his hands; and bears it with him▪ And there is no fighting against God but they fight against God, who resist his Ordinance, and go about to wrest the sword out of the hands of his An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nointed; whom (in the 105. <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.) he hath fenced about with a <hi>Nolite tang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:204961:36"/>re,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Touch not mine Annointed;</hi> for they that touch him, in the sense there prohibited, offer violence to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self: as he tells <hi>Samuel; They have not resisted or rejected thee, but me:</hi> so indisso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble is the conjunction of God and the King, and therefore, <hi>my Son,</hi> saith <hi>Salomon,</hi> fear both.</p>
                  <p>And this I press the rather, because too many of late, and some to this very day, that are great pretenders to the fear of God, do not in truth fear the King at all: and having for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent divested him of all his native and legall rights, one of which is his power; they look upon him (as the <hi>Philistines</hi> did upon <hi>Samson</hi> without his hair, in which his strength lay) with scorn and contempt, as if he were as weak and worthless as other men: but let them remember how God renewed <hi>Samsons</hi> strength, to revenge himself at last. Others (on the contrary) have seem'd so to fear the King, that they did not set the fear of God before their eyes; but as <hi>Ephestion</hi> said to <hi>Alexander, An
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204961:37"/>nescis te Imperatorem esse, &amp; leges dare non accipere?</hi> So these were ready to maintain that Paradox, or rather He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terodox, <hi>viz.</hi> That Kings may do what they list, and that they are to give Laws, but to live under none.</p>
                  <p>The plain truth is, both these are dangerous extremes; for he that in fearing God, excludes the King, is a pure hypocrite; and he that to promote the fear of the King, excludes the fear of God, is a prophane Parasite: and therefore, that you may the better avoid both these dangerous rocks, on which so many have made shipwrack of faith and a good conscience, let me entreat and exhort you, ever to joyn the fear of God and the King in your practice, as here <hi>Salomon</hi> doth in his Precept, <hi>My Son, fear God and the King</hi> for this is the right combination and conjunction.</p>
                  <p>And if, in the next place, we have regard to the order and disposition of these terms in the Text, we shall soon observe how God is first to be fear'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204961:37"/>and then the King: As Saint <hi>Peter</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>Whether it is meet to obey God, or man? judge ye.</hi> If God command one thing, and the King should command the contraay, then I say, Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is to be prefer'd; and yet let me tell you, that the King is not to be disobeyed: for a true Christian is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to a two-fold obedience; active, and passive: where the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands things lawfull, there yeild active obedience, and know that it is your duty to do them: but if he should command such a thing as you may not lawfully do, then you must not resist, but suffer patiently for your not doing it, and this is your passive obedience: and in both these you may still keep a good conscience: for as I said but now, though God be to be prefer'd, yet God will not have his Annointed to be disobeyed.</p>
                  <p>Indeed, some of the <hi>Heathens</hi> deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their king, as <hi>Belus, Saturn, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c. And the men of <hi>Tyre</hi> (<hi>Act.</hi> 12.) deified king <hi>Herod,</hi> crying out, The
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204961:38"/>voyce of God, and not of man. But I must tell you, that the same spirit of truth that bids you both to fear, and honour kings, forbids you to adore them. The surest and safest way is this w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>
                     <hi>Salomon</hi> chalks out in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> First, to fear God, and then the King: whose sacred Person, and Function (as Gods Ordinance) merits at our hands, so much honour, fear, and reverence, from our outward and inward man, as can possibly stand with the due fear of God: and to speak freely, I shall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be brought to believe, that he doth make a conscience of fearing God, as he ought, who doth not for Gods sake (being so frequently and so strictly commanded thereunto in both the <hi>Testaments,</hi>) make a conscience also of fearing the King, as the express image, and Annointed of God himself. Then, <hi>My Son, fear God, and the King;</hi> and in thy fear, observe both the fast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination and conjunction; and also the right order and disposition of them.</p>
                  <p>And so I have soon done with the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204961:38"/>Doctrin, which being so cleer in it self, and (like a Mathematicall Principle) shining by its own light, needs no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonstration: and give me leave to tell you, that hitherto I have contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted my self on purpose, that I might have somwhat the more time to spend on the fourth and last part of my Text, which in the distribution of the words into parts, I cal'd the Use and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in these words; <hi>And meddle not with them, &amp;c.</hi> And herein I shall a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enlarge my discourse (according to the <hi>mode</hi> of these <hi>reforming</hi> times, which commonly insists most upon <hi>Ʋse</hi> and <hi>Application</hi>) and for this once I shall do it the rather, because both the <hi>simple necessity</hi> of pressing this so seasonable a point, and also because I am convinc'd in reason that your <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian expectation</hi> call's upon me for it; and you shall have it <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>faithfully</hi> God willing.</p>
                  <p>The words in the <hi>Originall</hi> are of a <hi>large</hi> extent, and accordingly rendred by divers of the learned, diversly. For
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204961:39"/>
                     <hi>Pagnin</hi> out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> reads it, <hi>Et cum iterantibus iniquitates suas, ne misce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as te:</hi> that is, mingle not thy selfe with such as iterate their iniquities.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Caldee paraphrase</hi> hath it, <hi>Et cum stultis ne miscearis:</hi> that is, Be not thou mixt with fools.</p>
                  <p>Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and divers others translate it, <hi>Et cum mutatoribus,</hi> &amp;c. that is, Have thou nothing to do with such as are <hi>Changlings:</hi> and to shew that by <hi>Changlings</hi> he doth not mean such <hi>silly souls,</hi> as this too <hi>censorious,</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-credulous</hi> age call's <hi>Pure naturalls; Vatablus</hi> renders it, <hi>Et cum rerum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varum studiosis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Meddle not with such as are desirous of change:</hi> for all such for want of the <hi>true fear</hi> of God, do commonly prove most <hi>unnaturall</hi> to their <hi>king,</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> by <hi>inwardly</hi> and <hi>inordinately affecting,</hi> and outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>praeposterously effecting innovation,</hi> which is the greatest <hi>boutefeu</hi> in a <hi>setled estate;</hi> and accordingly rendred <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> so <hi>odious</hi> to <hi>Athens; Caesar</hi> to <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> himself to the <hi>Jewes,</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:204961:39"/>who generally look'd upon him as an <hi>Innovator,</hi> though God knows, and bears him witnesse, that he came not to <hi>destroy</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> but to <hi>fulfill</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>Our best and last Translation reads it, <hi>Meddle not with them that are seditious.</hi> Here then we have divers learned men of divers <hi>mindes,</hi> in rendring the words out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> context. Each of them abounds in his own sence; and each of these sences may be <hi>true;</hi> sure I am they want not good <hi>authority</hi> to <hi>justifie</hi> their severall read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And think not this strange; for I must tell you that the <hi>Holy tongue</hi> is but a very <hi>narrow</hi> language; and so one word in <hi>Hebrew</hi> ordinarily signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies divers things; as I could give you many instances, but that this in the Text is sufficient. And sure I am, that very good <hi>use</hi> may be made here of the <hi>severall readings;</hi> and since we are now upon that which I call the <hi>Ʋse</hi> of my Text, it will I hope be well worth the while to <hi>see</hi> and <hi>observe</hi> what wholsom <hi>Lessons</hi> we may learn from all, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:204961:40"/>of these four <hi>Translations.</hi> The first whereof reads it, <hi>Keep not company with customary sinners:</hi> and if you say, why not with them? The princely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> tells you the reason (<hi>Psal.</hi> 1.1.) where he saith, <hi>Blessed is the man that hath not walked in the counsell of the ungodly, nor stood in the way of sinners, nor sate in the chair of the scorner;</hi> which are but so many <hi>degrees</hi> of sinne: And it is most certain, that he who <hi>walkes</hi> in the <hi>counsell</hi> of the ungodly, and <hi>stands</hi> in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>sinners,</hi> will e're long come to <hi>complacency</hi> in sin, and so to take up his <hi>seat</hi> in the <hi>chair</hi> of the <hi>scorner.</hi> Or as <hi>Pagnin</hi> renders it, <hi>In cathedra pestilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> to signifie, that as an <hi>habituated sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> becomes at last a <hi>scorner;</hi> so a <hi>scorner</hi> like a <hi>pestilentiall chair,</hi> will mortally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect all that come near him: Then <hi>my sonne come not</hi> in his <hi>walke; stand not</hi> in his <hi>way; sit not</hi> in his <hi>seat;</hi> at least <hi>keep</hi> not <hi>unnecessary</hi> company with him; if either thou wouldst be <hi>safe</hi> here, or <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that touches pitch</hi> (saith <hi>Solomon</hi>)
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204961:40"/>
                     <hi>shall be defil'd.</hi> And as that proverb is true of <hi>materiall</hi> pitch, so it is much more of the <hi>morall:</hi> for some of the <hi>Ancients</hi> usually resemble a <hi>customary</hi> sinner to <hi>pitch,</hi> if he <hi>touches,</hi> he <hi>smutches</hi> you: then <hi>foule</hi> not your <hi>fingers</hi> with him; or which is <hi>worse,</hi> your <hi>souls.</hi> We read that as soon as the children of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were <hi>mingled</hi> with the <hi>Heathen ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi> they <hi>learn'd their works.</hi> And els<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where the <hi>Text</hi> saith, that <hi>of the froward thou shalt learn frowardness.</hi> But all cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomary <hi>sinners</hi> are <hi>froward,</hi> and that from their <hi>youth</hi> up: and we use to say, that the <hi>cloath</hi> that is <hi>dyed</hi> in the <hi>wool,</hi> will never lose it's <hi>colour:</hi> but all habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated <hi>sinners</hi> are dyed in the wool, if I may so speak; my meaning is, they wil <hi>hardly</hi> be <hi>reclaim'd: — Didicit nebulone parente,</hi> &amp;c. Like <hi>rotten apples</hi> they <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> the <hi>sound:</hi> Then say of them as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> did of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in evill; Into their secret let not my <hi>soule</hi> enter; My <hi>glory,</hi> be not thou joyned to their <hi>assembly,</hi> lest you become as <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>phanatique as themselves;</hi> for in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204961:41"/>this sence that of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true; <hi>Discit facere dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suescit videre:</hi> Here each <hi>Spectator</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an <hi>Actor,</hi> and <hi>acts</hi> a part by see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others <hi>play.</hi> The company and congregation of the <hi>wicked</hi> is the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils kingdome:</hi> and take heed what is said in <hi>Ecclesiastical history</hi> (that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> finding a <hi>pure Virgin</hi> in an <hi>impure place;</hi> he <hi>entred</hi> into her, and <hi>really pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd</hi> her, giving this reason to the <hi>Exorcist, Inveni eam in regno meo</hi>) be not true in you, that if the Devil find you in some corner-creeping <hi>Conventicle,</hi> or in any other <hi>evill company,</hi> or <hi>unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable place,</hi> he do not (as <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Soile</hi>) <hi>seize</hi> on you as so many <hi>straies;</hi> and <hi>enter</hi> you in his <hi>blacke booke</hi> as his <hi>proper goods</hi> and <hi>chattels;</hi> and so your <hi>latter end</hi> prove <hi>worse</hi> then your <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Divines</hi> well observe that some <hi>sins</hi> are <hi>common</hi> to all, as <hi>Anger;</hi> some <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> to some <hi>natures,</hi> as <hi>Ambition:</hi> and to some <hi>ages,</hi> as <hi>lust</hi> to <hi>youth, avarice</hi> to <hi>old age;</hi> some sins are neither <hi>naturall,</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:204961:41"/>nor <hi>unnaturall,</hi> as <hi>swearing;</hi> and some are against <hi>nature,</hi> as <hi>gluttony</hi> and <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenness:</hi> But of all sins it is most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that an <hi>habit</hi> once gotten, is <hi>sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome lost:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Cretes</hi> used this as that which they conceiv'd to be the heaviest <hi>curse, O may he fall into an ill habit!</hi> presuming that out of this, as it is the <hi>strongest snare</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> so it is <hi>extream difficult</hi> to <hi>extricate</hi> ones self; for the Devill hath <hi>praescription</hi> against all such; and <hi>Lawyers</hi> say that <hi>praescripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> hath the <hi>force</hi> of a <hi>Law:</hi> and S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome</hi> saith, that it was much for <hi>Jonas</hi> to <hi>recover</hi> out of the belly of that <hi>fish:</hi> but it is a great deal <hi>harder</hi> to recover out of a <hi>long custome</hi> of sinne; which in some respects is held <hi>morally impossible.</hi> And therefore I say with <hi>Solomon</hi> in the Text, <hi>My sonne, feare God, and the King, and meddle not with them</hi> that <hi>iter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their iniquities;</hi> so <hi>Pagnin</hi> reads it out of the <hi>Hebrew;</hi> and so you have the first Use.</p>
                  <p>But what <hi>Pagnin</hi> renders customary <hi>sinners,</hi> the <hi>Chaldee paraphrast</hi> reads,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:204961:42"/>
                     <hi>Fools; Et cum stultis ne miscearis;</hi> that is, <hi>Blend not thy selfe with fools:</hi> So that all such as for want of the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> keep ill company, and live in any ill custome, are <hi>starke fools:</hi> and though they be <hi>wise in their own eyes;</hi> yea, and passe in this world for <hi>great Politicians,</hi> as <hi>Achitophel</hi> in his time was call'd and counted an <hi>Oracle:</hi> yet as <hi>Thamar</hi> told <hi>Amnon,</hi> sinne will make them to be <hi>numbred</hi> among the <hi>fools of Israel:</hi> for they that are <hi>wise to do evill</hi> (as the <hi>Prophet</hi> speaks) but to <hi>do well</hi> have <hi>no understanding,</hi> are <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons fools;</hi> and that I may not seem to say it only, I will prove that they have all the <hi>characteristical notes,</hi> and remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable <hi>properties</hi> of <hi>fools.</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They are as <hi>ignorant,</hi> and <hi>indoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> as any <hi>fool: The oxe knowes his owner, and the Asse his Masters crib</hi> (saith the Lord in <hi>Isaiah</hi> 1.3.) but <hi>Israel doth not know, my people do not consider.</hi> The <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle</hi> saith, that they are <hi>alwayes learning, yet never come to the knowledg of the truth.</hi> And as <hi>Militides</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> could not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:204961:42"/>
                     <hi>tell</hi> whether his <hi>father</hi> or his <hi>mother brought</hi> him forth: So these <hi>know</hi> not, <hi>acknowledge</hi> not their <hi>holy Mother,</hi> the <hi>church,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> was the <hi>womb</hi> that <hi>bare</hi> them, and whose <hi>paps</hi> gave them <hi>suck.</hi> And it is wel if they acknowledge their <hi>father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, They are as <hi>self-will'd,</hi> and <hi>self-conceited,</hi> as any <hi>fool;</hi> tell them of their <hi>schisme, sacriledge, sedition, rebellion,</hi> and any other <hi>crime</hi> of which they stand <hi>guilty</hi> by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King:</hi> and they will not be <hi>convinced</hi> of their <hi>wickedness;</hi> and as <hi>Salomon</hi> speaks of a <hi>fool;</hi> they <hi>fear not</hi> til they <hi>feel</hi> the <hi>rod</hi> upon their own <hi>backs.</hi> And elsewhere the same <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>Seest thou a man that is wise in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool then of him;</hi> for of a <hi>natural</hi> fool God <hi>requires</hi> no more then he gives: but of these <hi>wilfull</hi> fools, he will <hi>exact</hi> a <hi>reason,</hi> and a <hi>rockoning</hi> of all their <hi>misdoings.</hi> And let me adde, He that is wise in his own conceit, is both a <hi>wise man,</hi> and a <hi>fool;</hi> a wise man in his own <hi>opinion,</hi> and a fool in <hi>all mens else.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Like <hi>fools,</hi> they are all for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204961:43"/>the <hi>present:</hi> as the <hi>Epicure</hi> cryed, <hi>Ʋtere temporibus, praesentibus utere rebus;</hi> they neither <hi>foresee,</hi> nor <hi>fear</hi> a <hi>change:</hi> they slight <hi>Christs counsell, Make unto you friends with the unrighteous Mammon, that they may receive you, failing, into their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting habitations.</hi> Though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be <hi>sensible,</hi> that <hi>daily</hi> and <hi>hourly,</hi> some of their <hi>boon-companions fall,</hi> yet they will not <hi>believe</hi> that they shall <hi>fail;</hi> And whereas <hi>Salomon</hi> sends such foolish <hi>idlesbies</hi> to the <hi>Ant</hi> or <hi>Pismire,</hi> (Prov. 6.) <hi>to consider her wayes,</hi> which <hi>hoords</hi> up <hi>provision</hi> in <hi>Summer,</hi> to <hi>support</hi> her in <hi>Winter:</hi> yet these use a <hi>foolish Proverb, Spend,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> will <hi>send;</hi> and so like <hi>Grashoppers,</hi> they <hi>sing,</hi> and <hi>sport</hi> away their <hi>pretious time,</hi> which the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> exhorteth all that are <hi>wise,</hi> by all means to <hi>redeem:</hi> And (as in the days of <hi>Noah</hi>) they <hi>sit down to eat and drink,</hi> till the main <hi>flood</hi> of Gods <hi>judgements overtakes,</hi> and <hi>overturns</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Like <hi>fools,</hi> they <hi>preferre trifles</hi> before <hi>treasure:</hi> It is well obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204961:43"/>
                     <hi>truly good,</hi> but what we <hi>cannot lose against our wills:</hi> such are <hi>God</hi> himself, and the <hi>good things</hi> which he hath <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared</hi> for us in <hi>his kingdom,</hi> where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>moth</hi> can <hi>consume,</hi> nor <hi>rust canker,</hi> nor <hi>thieves break in</hi> and <hi>steal:</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it is our <hi>Saviours</hi> counsel: <hi>Lay not up for your selves treasure on earth,</hi> because all <hi>earthly treasures</hi> are subject to one, or more of the <hi>mischiefs</hi> which I hinted but now: and yet these <hi>fools</hi> prefer a <hi>smoke</hi> of <hi>honour,</hi> a <hi>blast</hi> of <hi>fame,</hi> a <hi>dream</hi> of <hi>pleasure,</hi> a <hi>wedge</hi> of <hi>gold,</hi> a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonish garment,</hi> and the like <hi>transitory trash,</hi> before <hi>blessed Eternity.</hi> As when the <hi>French Cardinal</hi> was told by his <hi>ghostly father</hi> of the <hi>fulness of joy</hi> which is at Gods <hi>right hand,</hi> and <hi>pleasures for evermore;</hi> he <hi>fondly</hi> replied, that if he might <hi>choose,</hi> he would not leave his <hi>part</hi> in <hi>Paris</hi> for his <hi>part</hi> in <hi>Paradise:</hi> so these <hi>fools,</hi> (with that <hi>wealthy young Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> which our Lord advised to <hi>sell all,</hi> and <hi>give it to the poor,</hi> promising him <hi>treasure</hi> in <hi>heaven,</hi> but he went away <hi>sorrowfull,</hi> saith the Text) will not <hi>leave</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:204961:44"/>that on <hi>earth,</hi> which they cannot <hi>long keep,</hi> to <hi>receive</hi> that in <hi>heaven</hi> which they <hi>can never lose.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, and lastly, they are as <hi>mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> and <hi>mischievous,</hi> as any <hi>fools:</hi> It is <hi>pastime to a fool to do mischief,</hi> saith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> (Prov. 10.23.) <hi>Sin</hi> is his <hi>bable,</hi> he makes himself <hi>merry</hi> with it; and <hi>laetan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cum malefecerint,</hi> saith <hi>David;</hi> they <hi>rejoyce</hi> when they have <hi>ruin'd</hi> others; and <hi>laugh</hi> to see them <hi>lament. Belshaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> sumptuous feast was heighten'd by the <hi>Hogo</hi> of his delicious <hi>meats</hi> and <hi>drinks,</hi> as they were <hi>served</hi> in the <hi>vessels</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> No <hi>bowls</hi> to such <hi>Atheists,</hi> like a <hi>consecrated Challice</hi> to <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouse</hi> in; and no <hi>flesh</hi> so <hi>sweet,</hi> as that which the <hi>Eagle rob'd</hi> the <hi>Altar</hi> of: <hi>Money</hi> gotten by <hi>stinking</hi> means (as the <hi>Roman Emperour</hi> told his <hi>son</hi>) <hi>smells</hi> as <hi>sweet as honest gain: Lucri bonus est odor ex re qualibet;</hi> what care such <hi>fools,</hi> to <hi>rend</hi> and <hi>tear</hi> the <hi>Churches garments,</hi> so their <hi>own</hi> may be <hi>whole!</hi> or to <hi>build up</hi> their <hi>Babels,</hi> with the <hi>ruines</hi> of <hi>Sion;</hi> So that we may justly cry out with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:204961:44"/>Nostra suffodiunt, ut sua aedificent.</hi> And when they have <hi>rob'd</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of her <hi>patrimony,</hi> and the whole <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of her <hi>ancient plenty,</hi> then a <hi>self-denying Ordinance</hi> (when there is <hi>no more</hi> left to be <hi>taken away</hi>) not only makes <hi>satisfaction</hi> for the <hi>sacriledge,</hi> but <hi>justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies</hi> it to be no sin.</p>
                  <p>And how <hi>severely</hi> so ever <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>humane Laws censure oppression, extortion, homicide, murder, schisme, sedition, rebellion, treason;</hi> and if there be any thing <hi>worse,</hi> that these <hi>miscievous fools</hi> have <hi>omitted,</hi> yet it is now but <hi>wiping their mouths</hi> (with the <hi>Harlot</hi> in the <hi>Proverbs</hi>) and then they may say as <hi>truly</hi> as <hi>she doth,</hi> that they have <hi>done no wickedness.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>David</hi> assigns the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted cause</hi> of all these and all other <hi>evils,</hi> where he saith, <hi>That God comes not in all their thoughts;</hi> that is, they never think upon God as a <hi>just Judge:</hi> and so they <hi>fear</hi> not <hi>him;</hi> for if they did, they would <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>King</hi> too; for they that <hi>flatter</hi> themselves that they do <hi>fear</hi> the one, when yet they <hi>live</hi> in <hi>open opposition,</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:204961:45"/>and <hi>actuall rebellion</hi> against the <hi>other;</hi> are such <hi>fools</hi> in the Text, as you are <hi>charg'd</hi> not to <hi>mingle with: My Son, fear God and the King, and mingle not with fools;</hi> and so you <hi>see</hi> what <hi>use</hi> are you to make of the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphrase, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> context; and I call the <hi>second Ʋse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, in the <hi>third place,</hi> I told you that Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and <hi>Vatablus,</hi> render the words both to <hi>one</hi> sense; for <hi>cum mutatoribus,</hi> saith the <hi>one, Cum rerum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varum studiosis,</hi> saith the <hi>other: My son, fear God and the King, and meddle not with them that are desirous of change;</hi> and so <hi>one</hi> of our <hi>English translations</hi> reads it: and this by <hi>degrees</hi> brings the Text somewhat <hi>neerer</hi> to <hi>the Times,</hi> and more <hi>home</hi> to our <hi>selves;</hi> who (out of a <hi>desire of change</hi>) have of late run through <hi>all forms</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> and yet we have <hi>done</hi> nothing all the while, but what in us lay <hi>undone</hi> our selves, yea, they that took most <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>ringing</hi> of these <hi>changes,</hi> cannot yet give any <hi>satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to themselves for the <hi>present;</hi> and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:204961:45"/>much less can they <hi>assure</hi> themselves of any <hi>sound settlement</hi> for the <hi>future</hi> in the way they took; for as <hi>Tacitus</hi> (an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Historian,</hi> and great <hi>Statesman</hi> in his <hi>Time</hi>) gravely observes, All <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> in <hi>Government</hi> commonly do, <hi>cheat</hi> them most at <hi>last,</hi> who at <hi>first,</hi> did most <hi>desire</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>True it is, that this <hi>desire of change</hi> is in all by <hi>nature corrupted</hi> by the <hi>fall</hi> of our <hi>first parents,</hi> yea, even <hi>before</hi> the <hi>fall,</hi> the <hi>desire of change</hi> was the very <hi>first bait,</hi> with which the <hi>Devil angled</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Paradise;</hi> who, though they were <hi>created</hi> so <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> that they could not well be <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> yet as soon as the <hi>Serpent,</hi> or the <hi>Devil,</hi> or rather the <hi>Devil</hi> in the <hi>Serpent</hi> had <hi>suggested</hi> to them (<hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5.) <hi>Ye shall be as gods,</hi> &amp;c. they fell straight to <hi>nibbling;</hi> and so by <hi>eating</hi> of the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit,</hi> they have ever since <hi>set all their childrens teeth on edge,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet speaks.</p>
                  <p>It is <hi>hard</hi> for a good <hi>Historian</hi> to say on the sudden, how many several kinds
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:204961:46"/>of <hi>government</hi> were <hi>successively</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced among the <hi>Romans,</hi> by this <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satiable</hi> desire of <hi>change:</hi> It is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that they had <hi>Kings, Senators, Dictators, Tribunes, Consuls, Caesars,</hi> &amp;c. of some of which that jeer was started <hi>Vigilantissimum habuimus Proconsulē,</hi> &amp;c. We have now had a most <hi>vigilant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consul,</hi> for during the <hi>whole time</hi> of his <hi>Consulship,</hi> he never <hi>slept,</hi> meanig that he was <hi>elected</hi> at <hi>noon,</hi> and <hi>discarded</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>night.</hi> And by name, <hi>Galba, Otho,</hi> and <hi>Vitellius,</hi> three of their noted <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors,</hi> enjoyed their <hi>Dignity</hi> so <hi>short</hi> a <hi>space,</hi> that <hi>Apollonius</hi> wittily term'd them <hi>Theban Emperors;</hi> whereby he did <hi>insinuate,</hi> that as the <hi>Thebans</hi> were <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> but a <hi>short time;</hi> so these three continued <hi>Emperors</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> but a <hi>few Moneths:</hi> so <hi>inconstant</hi> was the <hi>humour</hi> of the gyddi-headed <hi>Romans</hi> in those days, that whom they had but newly <hi>set up,</hi> without any other reason then a mere <hi>affectation</hi> of <hi>novelty,</hi> and <hi>desire of change,</hi> they <hi>soon</hi> after <hi>pulled</hi> down. And no marvell, though the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:204961:46"/>
                     <hi>luxuriant Romans,</hi> that then knew lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of God, were so desirous of change, when as we finde Gods own people, the <hi>Iewes,</hi> not onely <hi>troubled</hi> with a <hi>spice,</hi> but <hi>desperately</hi> sick of this <hi>vertiginous</hi> disease: for they had their <hi>Dukes,</hi> or <hi>Leaders;</hi> their <hi>Judges;</hi> their <hi>Prophets;</hi> their <hi>High priests,</hi> their <hi>Kings;</hi> and for a time they had an <hi>Inter-reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and <hi>no king in Israel,</hi> beside divers other horrid <hi>jawfalls</hi> in government.</p>
                  <p>And if we draw neerer <hi>home,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice how <hi>praedominant</hi> in all ages this desire of change hath been in all <hi>parts</hi> of <hi>Christendome.</hi> What <hi>chopping</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> hath there been in <hi>Bohemia, Portugall, Polonia, Suevia,</hi> &amp;c. To which I might add the <hi>Low Countreys.</hi> And the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> hath so often <hi>chang'd</hi> their <hi>Governours,</hi> that at last their <hi>Estate</hi> was represent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an <hi>Asse,</hi> that having <hi>cast</hi> his <hi>Rider,</hi> turn'd his <hi>head backe,</hi> to see who would be so <hi>mad</hi> as to <hi>bestride</hi> him any more.</p>
                  <p>And even at this day the old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb <hi>(Mens humana novitatis avida)</hi>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:204961:47"/>is in nothing truer then in the point of government: for all <hi>States</hi> have their <hi>policies,</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> by <hi>Lawes:</hi> So it hath been, so it should be with us; and so it shall be I hope e're long: For a man were <hi>better</hi> to <hi>live</hi> among the most <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous</hi> people under heaven, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an <hi>absolute Tyranny,</hi> or <hi>arbitrary</hi> government. <hi>Lawes</hi> there must be; and <hi>lex à ligando,</hi> saith the <hi>Etymologer:</hi> It is call'd a <hi>law</hi> from <hi>binding;</hi> all <hi>lawes</hi> are like <hi>yokes:</hi> and this it was that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly rendred this <hi>Monarchy,</hi> though never so <hi>gracious</hi> in the <hi>publique admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration</hi> of <hi>justice</hi> both <hi>commutative,</hi> and <hi>distributive,</hi> yet to seem so <hi>grievous</hi> to them that <hi>feared</hi> neither <hi>God,</hi> nor the <hi>King:</hi> These (like so many <hi>beasts</hi>) find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves <hi>pinch'd</hi> with a <hi>yoke,</hi> I mean that of <hi>Gods Law,</hi> and the <hi>Kings,</hi> did never lin <hi>wincing</hi> and <hi>flinging,</hi> till they had <hi>cast it off;</hi> though by <hi>divine dispensation</hi> it hath since come to passe, that while they would not <hi>submit</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to Gods <hi>Ordinance,</hi> but went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by <hi>unlawfull</hi> meanes to <hi>extricate</hi>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:204961:47"/>themselves out of one <hi>pressure,</hi> they <hi>fell</hi> still into an <hi>heavier;</hi> like the <hi>fish</hi> in the proverb, that <hi>leaps</hi> out of the <hi>frying-pan</hi> into the <hi>fire.</hi> Just as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> told certain <hi>Graecians</hi> that had <hi>revolted</hi> from him to <hi>T. Quintus,</hi> the <hi>Roman Commander; Commutastis vestram catenam politiore quidem, sed longiore:</hi> that is, You have <hi>exchang'd</hi> your <hi>chain</hi> (meaning their <hi>servile</hi> condition) for one that at first sight seems a little better <hi>polished,</hi> but you will find it in time to be much more <hi>heavy,</hi> and <hi>lasting.</hi> And this was in effect the genuine meaning of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboams</hi> answer to his <hi>discontented</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, <hi>viz.</hi> That they should <hi>feel his little finger far heavier then his fathers loins;</hi> for whereas his <hi>father</hi> had onely <hi>whip'd</hi> them with <hi>scourges</hi> yet, he meant to <hi>scourge</hi> them with <hi>scorpions.</hi> Do you help me out in making the <hi>application,</hi> which the <hi>exigency</hi> of time <hi>constrains</hi> me to <hi>contract.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as when <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> (in the 36. chap. of <hi>Jeremy</hi>) had with a <hi>pen-knife cut the roul of parchment,</hi> which <hi>Baruch
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:204961:48"/>wrote</hi> from the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and <hi>cast it into the fire;</hi> then the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy</hi> took another <hi>roule,</hi> and gave it to <hi>Baruch</hi> the <hi>Scribe,</hi> and he wrote therein <hi>all</hi> the words of the <hi>book</hi> which <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> burnt in the fire; and <hi>there were added besides unto them many the like words;</hi> so that all he got by <hi>cutting</hi> and <hi>burning</hi> Gods <hi>will</hi> reveal'd in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting against both <hi>him,</hi> and his <hi>people,</hi> was onely to have more <hi>judgements</hi> first <hi>denounced,</hi> and then <hi>inflicted</hi> upon <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>his:</hi> So all they that <hi>fight</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Anointed,</hi> in stead of <hi>disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging,</hi> do the more <hi>intangle</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: and, like so many <hi>unruly Colts,</hi> get nothing by their <hi>disorderly</hi> desire of change, but onely to have the <hi>brand</hi> of Gods <hi>indignation fastned</hi> so much the <hi>deeper</hi> in their <hi>flesh.</hi> Thus they that <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly</hi> and <hi>wilfully resist</hi> Gods <hi>Ordinance,</hi> turn that which they reli'd upon as their <hi>likeliest</hi> remedy, into the <hi>worst</hi> of mischiefes that could have befallen them.</p>
                  <p>And yet as the <hi>Spies</hi> that were <hi>sent</hi>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:204961:48"/>to <hi>search</hi> the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> reported that it was <hi>a land that did eat up the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof.</hi> So it is pregnant in <hi>History,</hi> that very few Nations (out of the meer desire of change) will long endure any <hi>government,</hi> no nor scarce any <hi>Governour.</hi> The <hi>Belgicke Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> the <hi>Kirke</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va discipline,</hi> the <hi>New-Englanders Ʋto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> nor yet any <hi>setled</hi> in this Nation can please us long (who are yet in our wits) how then shall it <hi>satisfie</hi> the <hi>two Arch-enemies</hi> of all <hi>rule</hi> &amp; government, the <hi>Anabaptisticall Independents,</hi> and (the last <hi>extract</hi> of our <hi>Reformation</hi>) the <hi>Nonsensical Quakers,</hi> who would (if they had power to their wills) soon <hi>lay</hi> the <hi>axe</hi> to the <hi>root</hi> of all <hi>Magistracy,</hi> and <hi>Ministry</hi> whatsoever.</p>
                  <p>And what the <hi>prudent Italians</hi> say by way of proverb, that the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>man</hi> is <hi>short,</hi> of <hi>Kings shorter,</hi> and of <hi>Popes shortest</hi> of all: is now generally true of all <hi>forms</hi> of government; they are look'd upon as <hi>short-liv'd,</hi> and <hi>short lasting;</hi> and <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> because of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204961:49"/>this inordinate desire of change, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> whose <hi>principles</hi> are <hi>destructive</hi> of <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>settlement;</hi> in which both our <hi>being,</hi> as men, and our <hi>well-being,</hi> as Christians, do under <hi>God, and his Christ,</hi> chiefly <hi>consist.</hi> Yet I will be bold to say, that if those very <hi>Phanatiques,</hi> who are now so <hi>greedy</hi> of <hi>parity,</hi> and so <hi>fond</hi> of <hi>Anarchy,</hi> could be made <hi>sensible</hi> of the many <hi>miseries</hi> and <hi>mischiefs,</hi> which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally <hi>sprout</hi> from that <hi>bitter root,</hi> and were <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>live</hi> any <hi>considerable</hi> time in such a <hi>confusion,</hi> as they would bring us into; They would soon become more <hi>weary</hi> of that <hi>Calfe</hi> which now they do so unreasonably <hi>idolize,</hi> then ever any men were of the <hi>worst</hi> form of government that yet hath been heard of in any part of the habitable world.</p>
                  <p>Little do these men understand the <hi>deceitfulnesse</hi> of their own <hi>hearts,</hi> which like <hi>Africke,</hi> is ever producing <hi>new monsters:</hi> and <hi>the God of this world</hi> hath so <hi>blinded</hi> them, that they do little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204961:49"/>the <hi>corruption</hi> of their <hi>own nature;</hi> which (like <hi>some women</hi> with <hi>Childe</hi>) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>longs</hi> for such things, as being had, would <hi>destroy</hi> them. I cannot more fitly resemble these poor <hi>seduc'd</hi> soules then to <hi>sicke folks,</hi> labouring of a <hi>malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant feaver;</hi> who by reason that their <hi>palates</hi> are <hi>vitiated,</hi> are not able to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish,</hi> during the time, <hi>sweet</hi> from <hi>sowr,</hi> with whom nothing <hi>relishes,</hi> and to whom nothing is <hi>pleasing</hi> that the <hi>Physitian prescribes;</hi> because though the <hi>Physicke</hi> he administers be <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>wholsome,</hi> yet they cannot be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to thinke it so, having <hi>lost</hi> their <hi>taste.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then that I may a little <hi>open</hi> their <hi>eyes,</hi> I will shew them out of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> (in his excellent oration of Moderation to be us'd in divine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) what <hi>intolerable</hi> mischiefs are <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred</hi> by <hi>confusion, viz.</hi> In the <hi>aire thunderings;</hi> in the <hi>earth tremblings;</hi> in the <hi>sea storms,</hi> and <hi>shipwracks;</hi> in <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Families, strife</hi> and <hi>contention, Diseases</hi> in the <hi>body, death</hi> and <hi>damnation</hi> in the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204961:50"/>
                     <hi>soule;</hi> for the <hi>head</hi> of this <hi>Monster</hi> is the <hi>Devill;</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> is <hi>discontnt;</hi> the <hi>eyes, envy;</hi> the <hi>eares, evill reports;</hi> the <hi>tongue, sedition;</hi> the <hi>hands, rapine</hi> and <hi>bloodshed;</hi> and the <hi>feet woe,</hi> and <hi>destruction.</hi> Then <hi>my sonnes, fear God, and the king;</hi> and <hi>meddle not with them that are desirous of change;</hi> because you are now <hi>convinc'd</hi> that they are like the <hi>fruit</hi> we call <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> which are never <hi>good,</hi> till they be <hi>rotten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Mythologist</hi> appositely illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates this <hi>ill affection</hi> in a <hi>fable</hi> to this effect: Upon a time the <hi>Frogs</hi> petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd <hi>Jupiter</hi> to grant them a <hi>King;</hi> in condescention whereunto he tumbled among them a <hi>Log:</hi> and after they had leap'd a while both on it, and about it, and found it to be <hi>insensible;</hi> then they <hi>petition'd</hi> again for a <hi>King</hi> that should be <hi>active</hi> and <hi>stirring;</hi> and thereupon he sent them a <hi>Crane,</hi> which strait fell to <hi>pecking them up:</hi> The <hi>morall</hi> whereof shews plainly, that nothing can long give satisfaction to this natural desire
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204961:50"/>of change; whether the <hi>Governour,</hi> and <hi>government</hi> be a <hi>log,</hi> or a <hi>Crane; passive</hi> or <hi>active; clement</hi> or <hi>cruell; grievous</hi> or <hi>gracious;</hi> yet such as desire change will soon <hi>disrelish</hi> both <hi>him</hi> and <hi>it;</hi> not so much because he is <hi>unfit</hi> to rule, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are <hi>unwilling</hi> to obey, either <hi>him,</hi> or any <hi>other:</hi> and though they sometimes are so <hi>well</hi> that they know not how to <hi>better</hi> themselves, and their <hi>condition,</hi> yet will they leave no <hi>stone</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>unsettle</hi> and <hi>alter it:</hi> and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be <hi>inslav'd</hi> by a <hi>bad,</hi> then <hi>constant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endure</hi> a <hi>good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, as in the <hi>Poeticall fable, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> could never <hi>fit</hi> a <hi>garment</hi> to the <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> because <hi>she</hi> is ever <hi>waxing</hi> or <hi>waining:</hi> so neither can any <hi>form</hi> of <hi>government</hi> long <hi>suit</hi> with the <hi>humour</hi> of the people, whose <hi>restless</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of <hi>change</hi> is such, that (like so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>children</hi>) they commonly <hi>cry loudest</hi> for they know not what; and being <hi>rebellious</hi> by nature since the <hi>fall,</hi> they <hi>rise up</hi> against all <hi>Power,</hi> as it is <hi>power;</hi> not considering <hi>that all power is of God;</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:204961:51"/>and therefore is to be <hi>submitted</hi> to, not only for <hi>fear</hi> (as the <hi>Apostle</hi> speaks in the 13. Chapter to the <hi>Romans</hi>) but <hi>even for conscience sake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft,</hi> (saith God by his <hi>Prophet</hi>) and <hi>mankind</hi> being <hi>bewitched</hi> with it; it falls out for the most part with us, as it doth with <hi>Witches;</hi> that <hi>chain</hi> (saith <hi>Delrio</hi>) which the <hi>Devil</hi> makes the <hi>Witch</hi> believe to be of <hi>gold,</hi> she finds (when the <hi>mist</hi> is <hi>dispers'd</hi> to be but <hi>copper</hi> and <hi>counterfeit;</hi> and seeing her self <hi>deluded,</hi> she grows <hi>discontented;</hi> yet for want of <hi>Grace, goes</hi> on still, as the <hi>Devils drudge,</hi> to the utter <hi>undoing</hi> of her <hi>self</hi> and <hi>others:</hi> Thus, what some few yeares ago we <hi>set up,</hi> and both <hi>approved</hi> and <hi>applauded;</hi> yet now, when we have even <hi>tired</hi> our selves in the <hi>ways of wickedness,</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction hath given us understanding;</hi> we do <hi>justly</hi> both <hi>reject,</hi> and <hi>resist,</hi> as finding our selves <hi>cheated, beggar'd,</hi> and utterly <hi>ruin'd</hi> by our <hi>own inventions,</hi> I mean, this <hi>desire of change:</hi> but the Lord in mercy <hi>change our desires</hi> before it be too late;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204961:51"/>and give us all grace <hi>conscientiously</hi> to follow wise <hi>Salomons</hi> counsell in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> To <hi>fear God and the King;</hi> and not <hi>meddle with them that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of change.</hi> And thus I have done with the third reading of the <hi>words</hi> out of the <hi>Originall,</hi> and the <hi>Ʋse</hi> you are to make of it.</p>
                  <p>But our last <hi>Translation</hi> runs, <hi>Meddle not with them that are seditious;</hi> for all such, <hi>qua</hi> such, <hi>fear</hi> neither <hi>God</hi> nor the <hi>King;</hi> and therefore were there no other reason, yet this one is enough to <hi>deterre</hi> you from <hi>meddling</hi> with them: but there be many more, as you shall see ere I have done, which I will touch onely with a light <hi>Pencil,</hi> and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sedition is defin'd to be an insolent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of self-conceited subjects, from such lawfull power as God hath set over them.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (in the 13. Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> 2.) hath this <hi>Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Canon,</hi> Let <hi>every soul be subject to the higher powers;</hi> where speaking in the plurall number, of <hi>powers,</hi> he implyes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:204961:52"/>that there be <hi>more</hi> then <hi>one;</hi> divers <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>government,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> of them are <hi>powers:</hi> And the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in each, hath an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to its <hi>correlative;</hi> and the <hi>higher</hi> the <hi>power</hi> is, the more is our <hi>subjection</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged thereunto: But by our <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws,</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>highest power,</hi> and all others that bear any rule among, and over us, are <hi>subordinate</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> (in the second Chapter of his first <hi>Epistle Generall</hi>) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts <hi>positively,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Supreme;</hi> and the <hi>Philosopher</hi> will allow <hi>in unoquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que genere,</hi> but <hi>unum summum.</hi> So that the <hi>co-ordination</hi> which some seditious persons have so <hi>fiercely</hi> mantain'd of late, is <hi>point-blanck</hi> against, not onely <hi>Religion,</hi> but <hi>right reason.</hi> And as for the <hi>new coyn'd</hi> distinctions of the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistorian schismaticks,</hi> whereby they have done their utmost to <hi>enervate</hi> the <hi>Kings Supremacy;</hi> and with the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> in King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. dayes, who <hi>set up</hi> his <hi>Cap</hi> above the <hi>Crown;</hi> these would <hi>set up</hi> their <hi>Kirks</hi> above the <hi>King; Popery</hi> and <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> both in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:204961:52"/>
                     <hi>opinions</hi> and <hi>practice, differ</hi> in many things onely in <hi>terms</hi>) by a <hi>Jesuiticall</hi> evasion of <hi>coordination,</hi> and <hi>suhordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> of the <hi>Kings politick</hi> capacity, and his <hi>personall;</hi> of <hi>major singulis,</hi> and <hi>minor universis,</hi> &amp;c. These, I say, and such like <hi>distinctions,</hi> are but the <hi>brain-sick fictions</hi> of <hi>seditious Malecontents,</hi> who cast off the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> and when they have <hi>wounded</hi> their own <hi>consciences,</hi> and all theirs, whom by such <hi>decoys</hi> they have <hi>drawn</hi> in to side with them, in stead of <hi>seriously repenting,</hi> they <hi>laugh</hi> out some such <hi>new-fangled distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and think therewith to <hi>salve</hi> up the matter. But the <hi>Casuists</hi> say perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily, <hi>Non est distinguendum, ubi lex ipsa non distinguit:</hi> we must not <hi>distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish,</hi> where the <hi>law</hi> it self <hi>distinguishes</hi> not. But the <hi>Law</hi> in this case <hi>distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishes</hi> not, as they know very well; and now you know it too, <hi>Meddle not with them;</hi> whom you <hi>have,</hi> and will <hi>find</hi> like the <hi>Trojane Horse,</hi> whose <hi>belly</hi> was <hi>lined</hi> with <hi>armed men,</hi> who first <hi>surpized,</hi> and then <hi>sacked Troy: Et ab uno disce omnes.</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:204961:53"/>And that I may the better take you of from <hi>meddling</hi> with the <hi>seditious</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, give me leave to <hi>use</hi> and <hi>urge</hi> two sorts of <hi>Arguments:</hi> the one I will draw from the due consideration of the <hi>bad causes;</hi> the other of the <hi>sad consequences</hi> of <hi>sedition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The former, which I take from the <hi>causes</hi> of <hi>sedition</hi> looks upon them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>primary</hi> and <hi>efficient,</hi> or <hi>secondary</hi> and <hi>subservient.</hi> The <hi>primary cause</hi> of <hi>sedition,</hi> is the <hi>Devil;</hi> who as he works effectually in all <hi>the children of disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> so he ceaseth not to <hi>stir</hi> them up continually by his <hi>perverse</hi> and pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>suggestions,</hi> and <hi>infusions</hi> sometimes <hi>secretly</hi> and <hi>unsuspectedly</hi> to undermine, and sometimes <hi>openly</hi> and <hi>impudently</hi> to <hi>rise up</hi> against the <hi>civil</hi> Magistrate, who is <hi>Custos utriusque tabulae;</hi> and whom God hath so often expresly <hi>commanded us</hi> to <hi>love, honour, serve, fear, obey, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, preserve, maintain, fight for;</hi> and in a word, <hi>To render unto him all his dues,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> expresseth it, and presseth us, in the 13. to the <hi>Romans</hi> 7. <hi>Render
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:204961:53"/>therefore to all their dues, Tribute to whom tribute is due, custom to whom custom, fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour;</hi> but both, <hi>tribute,</hi> and <hi>custom,</hi> and <hi>fear,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> are the <hi>Kings due;</hi> God himself, who is Lord <hi>paramount,</hi> and the onely <hi>great proprietary,</hi> hath <hi>made</hi> and <hi>declar'd</hi> them so. And so we must not think in any of these kinds, that we <hi>give</hi> the <hi>King</hi> some-what that we may <hi>justly keep,</hi> as if it were <hi>ours;</hi> but we must <hi>pay</hi> them unto <hi>him,</hi> as a <hi>debt due</hi> unto <hi>him:</hi> And to signifie this the more plainly, St. <hi>Paul</hi> there doth not say <hi>Date,</hi> but <hi>Reddite.</hi> And our <hi>Saviour</hi> himself, to shew that <hi>Christian liberty</hi> will stand well enough with <hi>civill subjection,</hi> useth the self same term (in <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21.) <hi>Render there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto Caesar the things which are Caesars, and unto God the things that are Gods:</hi> where he joyns God and <hi>Caesar</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to shew that both of them have their <hi>distinct rights;</hi> and that we must <hi>pay</hi> them to <hi>both</hi> accordingly: and that if we <hi>defraud,</hi> or <hi>detain</hi> the <hi>dues</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> we must be <hi>responsible</hi> to the <hi>censure</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:204961:54"/>and <hi>vengeance</hi> of the <hi>other;</hi> which I <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly</hi> entreat the seditious to <hi>chew</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>The later, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>ministerial causes</hi> of <hi>sedition</hi> are many and many: and therefore for brevities sake I will hint but some few of them, which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be the <hi>chief,</hi> that you may <hi>know</hi> them to <hi>avoid</hi> them. And such are</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Evill company,</hi> and <hi>counsell;</hi> these the <hi>Devil</hi> useth as his <hi>bellows</hi> to <hi>blow</hi> the <hi>coals</hi> into a <hi>flame,</hi> which he first <hi>kindled,</hi> and <hi>set on fire. Tully</hi> (in his 3<seg rend="sup">d.</seg> Oration against <hi>Verres</hi>) gives him this <hi>ill chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, viz.</hi> That he was <hi>Malus civis,</hi> a bad Citizen; <hi>improbus Consull,</hi> a worse Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul, because like <hi>Sylla,</hi> he <hi>look'd</hi> more at his own <hi>private gain,</hi> then on the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good;</hi> and <hi>seditiosus homo,</hi> a sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, that is, one that loved to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender strife, and raise tumults by <hi>ill arts</hi> among the people, then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> (in his fifth book <hi>De republica</hi>) makes both <hi>luxuriancy</hi> in <hi>wealth</hi> to be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204961:54"/>
                     <hi>one procreating cause</hi> of sedition: (as when <hi>horses</hi> are <hi>pamper'd,</hi> and proven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der prick'd, they grow <hi>head-strong</hi> and <hi>unruly</hi>) And <hi>extream poverty</hi> and <hi>beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging necessity</hi> to be another. For <hi>Durum telum necessitas:</hi> and our Proverb is, that <hi>Necessity</hi> hath no <hi>law:</hi> which holds not onely in this, that <hi>poor folkes</hi> seldome have the benefit of the <hi>Law</hi> for want of monies to <hi>fee</hi> the <hi>Lawyers</hi> (among whom might commonly overcomes right. <hi>Absque dativo accusativo, Roma favere negat)</hi> But it holds in this respect too, because when men are in so <hi>low</hi> a condition, that they cannot possibly live in a <hi>worse,</hi> then they grow <hi>male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> and seditious, that by <hi>imbroiling all</hi> they may <hi>enrich</hi> themselves; what care they in such a <hi>desperate humour</hi> to set o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens <hi>houses</hi> on <hi>fire,</hi> while they by the <hi>help</hi> of the <hi>light</hi> can <hi>see</hi> the <hi>better</hi> how to <hi>run away</hi> with their <hi>goods?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which three, I might add <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> in government; when it meets with <hi>faction, self-conceit, prejudice,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>imbitter'd</hi> stich and <hi>contempt</hi> in the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204961:55"/>
                     <hi>common people</hi> of the <hi>Higher powers;</hi> are so many <hi>procreating causes</hi> of <hi>sedition,</hi> which like an <hi>unlucky constellation</hi> ever <hi>portends evill,</hi> and never <hi>produces</hi> any <hi>good</hi> in a <hi>setled State:</hi> Wherefore since all the <hi>causes</hi> of sedition are so <hi>evill</hi> and <hi>ominous, My sonne, meddle not with them that are seditious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And yet let me tell you, that the <hi>conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> of sedition are far worse: For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sedition is ever <hi>turbulent,</hi> it sets all in an <hi>uproar;</hi> as you may observe (in <hi>Acts</hi> 19.) when <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and the <hi>Craftsmen,</hi> who were their <hi>Crafts-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> saw their <hi>gain</hi> by <hi>Diana's silver shrines go down,</hi> by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching that they were no Gods which are made with hands; they strait <hi>rose up</hi> and like <hi>mad men</hi> ran to and fro, crying <hi>Great is Diana of the Ephesians,</hi> till they had soon put the whole <hi>Citie</hi> in <hi>combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> and <hi>confusion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2<seg rend="sup">ly.</seg> Sedition <hi>fills</hi> all places with <hi>war</hi> and <hi>bloud-shed;</hi> as both <hi>Homer</hi> illustrate in his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; &amp; <hi>Josephus (de Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Judaico</hi>) shews at large the <hi>barbarism</hi>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:204961:55"/>and <hi>bloody-mindedness</hi> of the <hi>factious</hi> and <hi>seditious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the <hi>needless quarrels,</hi> and <hi>groundless contentions</hi> of the <hi>seditious,</hi> how slight so ever they seem at first, yet many times they (like <hi>snow-balls</hi> by <hi>long rolling</hi>) grow <hi>vast</hi> and <hi>formidable:</hi> and the <hi>incredible Story</hi> which <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> tells of the <hi>one,</hi> became <hi>authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique</hi> and <hi>demonstrable,</hi> both formerly in the City of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Syracusa;</hi> and of late, in the <hi>Fisherman</hi> of <hi>Naples;</hi> not to instance our own <hi>sad</hi> experience at <hi>home,</hi> which can hardly be <hi>parallel'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Sedition</hi> many times <hi>ends</hi> in the <hi>conflagration</hi> of whole <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> as <hi>Virgil</hi> Elegantly <hi>portrays</hi> it in that of <hi>Troy; Jam{que} faces, &amp; Saxa vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, furor arma ministrat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Howe'r the <hi>seditious</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <hi>work</hi> like so many <hi>Moles,</hi> and <hi>Pyoners under ground;</hi> and like the <hi>Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Traytors</hi> in <hi>Vauts,</hi> (as by jealous <hi>whispers,</hi> adle <hi>shakings</hi> of the head, <hi>shrugs</hi> and other <hi>discontented</hi> postures; scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd <hi>libels,</hi> scandalous <hi>invectives,</hi> puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204961:56"/>
                     <hi>Pasquils, ambiguous</hi> answers to <hi>State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demands;</hi> and a thousand other wayes of <hi>undermining</hi>) yet at last they <hi>blow up</hi> all with a <hi>furiousness,</hi> surmounting that of <hi>Gunpowder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixthly, The plausible <hi>Prologues</hi> and <hi>pretenses</hi> of the <hi>seditious,</hi> do usually <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine</hi> in a <hi>tragicall Catastrophe,</hi> as the <hi>factions</hi> between the <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi> though at first but <hi>personall</hi> (those engaging on the one side, these on the other) <hi>over-ran</hi> almost all <hi>Italy</hi> in the <hi>conclusion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seventhly, <hi>Sedition</hi> is most <hi>impetuous;</hi> &amp; accordingly compar'd to such things as are most <hi>active</hi> &amp; <hi>destructive:</hi> as to the <hi>Sea breaking in,</hi> which carries all before it. So to a <hi>fire breaking out,</hi> and a <hi>plague</hi> of <hi>pestilence; Incipit ab uno, inficit omnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lastly, <hi>Sedition</hi> is a <hi>pernicious evil; Thucidydes</hi> stiles it, All kind of <hi>evils.</hi> And <hi>nullam malum perniciosius,</hi> saith <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> in his book last quoted; There is no <hi>evil</hi> more <hi>pernicious</hi> then <hi>sedition;</hi> for this <hi>divides,</hi> yea, and <hi>discorps</hi> a <hi>City: Division</hi> commonly ushers in <hi>destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:204961:56"/>And accordingly, when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> would curse the professed enemies of <hi>God,</hi> he began there <hi>Divide, Destrue; Divide their tongues, and destroy them, O Lord, for I have seen violence and strife in the City.</hi> And all these <hi>evils</hi> of <hi>punishment</hi> have in one <hi>part</hi> or other in some <hi>measure befallen</hi> us, in one or other of the three <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> since so many of us for want of the true <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God and the King, meddled</hi> with those whom we could not choose but know to be <hi>seditious,</hi> by their first <hi>kindling</hi> the <hi>coals,</hi> and their <hi>blowing</hi> up the <hi>quarrel</hi> betwixt King and Parliament: till to <hi>gratifie</hi> their own <hi>factions,</hi> and <hi>satisfie themselves</hi> and their own <hi>friends,</hi> they had brought us to this <hi>generall want,</hi> &amp; <hi>woes,</hi> through <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> (I mean the true <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> as it was here <hi>esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>soundest</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>neerest</hi> in <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> to the <hi>Primtive,</hi> of all the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches</hi> in <hi>Christendom;</hi> and in stead of this <hi>one,</hi> which was truly <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, Catholique</hi> and <hi>Apostolique,</hi> we are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204961:57"/>now like <hi>Corinth,</hi> where any <hi>Religion</hi> under heaven may be found, save on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Of <hi>Law,</hi> for we have had for many years, no <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>old</hi> and well known <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> but only an <hi>Arbitrary government, chang'd</hi> like an <hi>Almanack,</hi> from year to year, at the <hi>will</hi> of our <hi>new Lords pro temporum ratione.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Of <hi>liberty;</hi> which hath been no other of late, but meer <hi>vassallage,</hi> for if we did not what out <hi>Task-masters</hi> listed to <hi>impose</hi> upon us, <hi>bonds</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonments waited for us,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of himself in the 20. of the <hi>Acts</hi>) <hi>in every place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Of <hi>Property,</hi> for no man all this while, could with any <hi>assurance,</hi> call any thing he had <hi>his own;</hi> It was but starting up a <hi>Covenant, Ingagement,</hi> or an <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>abjuration</hi> for all; or <hi>pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a <hi>quarrell</hi> with any <hi>particular</hi> person, and then he must be <hi>imprison'd, pillag'd</hi> and <hi>plunder'd</hi> without <hi>bail</hi> or <hi>main-prize.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Of <hi>peace;</hi> for when we did but <hi>pursue</hi> in our <hi>actions,</hi> or but <hi>petition</hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:204961:57"/>and <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>publike</hi> peace out of never so good <hi>affection,</hi> we were <hi>voted Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, Malignants, Ill-affected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Of <hi>plenty,</hi> for this <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> which for <hi>affluence</hi> in all kinds, was the <hi>envy</hi> &amp; <hi>admiration</hi> of the whole earth, are now <hi>reduc'd</hi> to such <hi>extreme necessity</hi> through the <hi>continuance</hi> of the <hi>war,</hi> and <hi>maintainance</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> that had no <hi>enemy;</hi> and the <hi>generall decay</hi> of <hi>trade,</hi> (there being no considerable <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation</hi> or <hi>exportation</hi> of <hi>goods</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years,) that the <hi>rich</hi> are not <hi>able</hi> to <hi>succour</hi> and <hi>support</hi> the <hi>poor</hi> which are become <hi>innumerable, quo ad nos;</hi> and the <hi>poor</hi> must, e're long, either <hi>fall</hi> upon the <hi>rich</hi> mens <hi>coffers,</hi> or <hi>eat up</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>carkasses.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seventhly, Of <hi>Truth, Justice, Charity, King,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himself; all which (save that there be a <hi>few names</hi> in <hi>Sardi's;</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> hath an <hi>election of grace</hi> in all <hi>places</hi> and <hi>ages</hi>) seem among us, like <hi>materia prima,</hi> at this day, to have no other <hi>being</hi> then in <hi>terms.</hi> Indeed, all this while, the <hi>prevailing factions</hi> have
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204961:58"/>taken the Name of <hi>God</hi> into their mouths (as the Prophet speaks in the 50. <hi>Psalm</hi>) though the love of their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> made them <hi>hate to be reformed:</hi> and they had some <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>godliness,</hi> though in their works they <hi>deny'd</hi> the <hi>power</hi> thereof. And now, if you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how, and why all these, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other <hi>unspeakable evils</hi> have laien upon us so <hi>heavy,</hi> and under most of which we languish at this day? you are fully answered in the <hi>Text:</hi> It is first for your <hi>customary</hi> sins yet <hi>unrepented</hi> of; secondly, for your <hi>fooling,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> useth the <hi>term</hi> in this book of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs;</hi> (Some mens <hi>success</hi> in their <hi>sins</hi> hath <hi>fool'd</hi> them into down-right <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme</hi>): thirdly, for you <hi>exorbitant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of change,</hi> which hath thus by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees <hi>allay'd</hi> your <hi>pure wine</hi> with <hi>water,</hi> and turned all your <hi>ancient treasure</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>trash</hi> and <hi>trumpery;</hi> and especially, for your <hi>meddling</hi> with the <hi>seditious,</hi> whom you first <hi>encourag'd, countenanc'd, assisted, protected,</hi> and <hi>sided with,</hi> against all that was <hi>cal'd God</hi> among us: &amp; now
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204961:58"/>you <hi>reap</hi> the <hi>fruits,</hi> and <hi>eat</hi> the <hi>earnings</hi> of your own <hi>heads, hearts,</hi> and <hi>hands;</hi> which I hope will be a <hi>fair warning</hi> to you, and all generations yet to come, to fear God and the King, as you are here exhorted, and to meddle no more with the <hi>seditious,</hi> for the <hi>many, weighty</hi> reasons already alledg'd. And yet, if we look wel upon the words, we shall find all these, and <hi>more,</hi> and <hi>worse,</hi> partly <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd</hi> in the <hi>close</hi> of the Text, which urgeth <hi>this; For their destruction comes sodainly;</hi> and <hi>therefore my son, meddle not with them;</hi> and partly <hi>implied,</hi> when he <hi>queries thus, And who knows the end thereof?</hi> Of either of which give me leave to speak but a word or two more, and no more.</p>
                  <p>It is observable that the Scripture seldome speaks of the <hi>death</hi> of Gods <hi>servants,</hi> but either with some <hi>allay</hi> of the <hi>bitternesse,</hi> and acrimony thereof; and thus it is call'd not a death, but a <hi>departing,</hi> a <hi>dissolution,</hi> a <hi>sleep,</hi> a <hi>resting under hope,</hi> a <hi>refreshing,</hi> &amp;c. Or with some <hi>addition</hi> either of honour, as <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:204961:59"/>in the sight of the Lord is the death of his Saints:</hi> Or of <hi>happiness,</hi> as <hi>Blessed are the dead that dye in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. But when it speaks of the death of the <hi>wicked</hi> (such as are all <hi>customary, obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and <hi>impenitent sinners;</hi> All <hi>atheisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal fools;</hi> all <hi>Innovators</hi> that are <hi>desirous of change;</hi> and all <hi>schismatical</hi> and <hi>sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> persons) then it useth for the most part some <hi>tearms</hi> of <hi>horrour</hi> and <hi>torment</hi> by way of <hi>aggravation:</hi> And so they are said <hi>not to dye the common death of all men;</hi> but to be <hi>drown'd in destruction and perdition;</hi> to be <hi>swept away with the bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of destruction;</hi> to <hi>perish in the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saying of Core:</hi> And here <hi>their destruction comes sodainly;</hi> which shews that there is both <hi>violence</hi> in the <hi>motion,</hi> since it is not death, but destruction; and also <hi>celerity</hi> in the <hi>execution</hi> of it; Since their destruction comes, it's spoken in the <hi>present</hi> tense, and comes <hi>sodainly,</hi> and shall both take them away <hi>unprepar'd,</hi> and leave them no way to <hi>escape.</hi> As I might instance first in the <hi>generall,</hi> in <hi>Cora, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and the <hi>two
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:204961:59"/>hundred and fifty Princes of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, men of renown,</hi> and all that sided with them in that <hi>sedition</hi> which they rais'd against <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> (Gods <hi>Magistrate</hi> and <hi>High priest</hi>) who were all <hi>swallowed up quicke</hi> by the <hi>earth open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> as we read in <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. which may serve as a <hi>warning piece</hi> to us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And next in many <hi>particulars;</hi> for fair-spoken <hi>Absolom</hi> (who seditiously assembled the mighty men of <hi>Israel</hi> together against his <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>Civill father,</hi> King <hi>David</hi>) was sodainy <hi>twit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> up in the <hi>forke</hi> of a <hi>Tree,</hi> and so left <hi>hanging</hi> between <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So <hi>Zimri</hi> who at first <hi>conspir'd</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and then <hi>slew</hi> his <hi>Master,</hi> (King <hi>Elah</hi> (in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16.) soon after <hi>burnt himselfe</hi> to death in the close of the same Chapter.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Sheba, a man of Belial,</hi> for <hi>blowing</hi> the <hi>trumpet</hi> of <hi>Sedition,</hi> saying, <hi>We have no part in David, every man to his tents, O Israel</hi> (in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1.) was soon as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>beheaded</hi> by the <hi>men of Abel;</hi> and his <hi>head</hi> was <hi>cast over</hi> the <hi>walls</hi> to <hi>Joab,</hi> in
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204961:60"/>the end of the same Chapter. Not to multiply Scripture instances; how e're they that are desirous of change, and seditious men, may <hi>flatter</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in a <hi>seeming impurity;</hi> yet our own <hi>Chronicles,</hi> yea our own <hi>sad experience</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly testifie this truth, That <hi>their destruction comes sodainly:</hi> How many <hi>memorable</hi> and <hi>fearful examples</hi> of <hi>divine justice</hi> in this kind have we seen of late, whose <hi>punishment</hi> was as <hi>notorious</hi> as their <hi>sin.</hi> Then <hi>my son, meddle not with them;</hi> for (whether you look into the <hi>Law</hi> of God, or into the <hi>Civill</hi> Law, which is the law of <hi>Nations;</hi> or into the <hi>Common Law</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) still you will finde, that their destruction comes so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly: and one would think that is <hi>bad</hi> enough; and yet I must tell you, or rather the Text it self tells you, that there is a great deal <hi>more</hi> and <hi>worse</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind: For my Text is like a <hi>Bee</hi> that hath both <hi>honey</hi> and a <hi>sting.</hi> It begins (as you have heard) with the <hi>feare of God, and the King,</hi> which is all honey: but if <hi>Changlings</hi> and <hi>seditious</hi> persons
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204961:60"/>(of which the world is too full) will none of this sweet and soveraign ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I mean the fear, which I spake of but now; yet whether they <hi>will or no,</hi> they shall <hi>feel</hi> the <hi>sting;</hi> for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction comes sodainly; there is their <hi>temporall</hi> death: And <hi>who knows the end thereof</hi> (saith <hi>Solomon.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Quis scit</hi> is a <hi>Nemo scit:</hi> This <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogation</hi> is aequipollent to a simple <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation:</hi> as if he had said, No man <hi>knows</hi> it while he <hi>lives</hi> here; though this <hi>Quis scit</hi> hath begotten <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>intricate questions;</hi> yet no man <hi>alive</hi> is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle</hi> and <hi>resolve</hi> them; but the <hi>sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> nor they neither till (as it is said of <hi>Judas, Act.</hi> 1.) they <hi>go to their own place;</hi> and that you may not go <hi>thither</hi> for company, let me counsel you, as <hi>Moses</hi> doth the <hi>Israelites</hi> (<hi>Numb.</hi> 16.) <hi>Depart from the tents of these wicked men, &amp; touch nothing of theirs, lest that you perish in all their sins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And (which I must not forget) this question of <hi>Solomon, Who knows the end thereof? implies</hi> that there is <hi>more</hi> in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204961:61"/>destruction of the seditious, then a <hi>meer</hi> temporal death; for all men <hi>know</hi> the <hi>end</hi> thereof; it hints what St. <hi>John</hi> calls the <hi>second death,</hi> viz. <hi>Condemnation,</hi> or in plain English, <hi>Damnation,</hi> which is aeternal, <hi>à parte post,</hi> as the learned speak: and <hi>who knows the end thereof?</hi> The <hi>worme</hi> (saith the Prophet) <hi>never dyes,</hi> and the <hi>fire</hi> never <hi>goes out.</hi> Then as you <hi>love</hi> your <hi>lives,</hi> and the <hi>life</hi> of your lives, your dearest <hi>souls;</hi> and the <hi>soul</hi> of your souls, <hi>salvation</hi> it self, <hi>med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with them:</hi> and so I <hi>conclude</hi> as I <hi>began, My sonne, fear God, and the King, and meddle not with them that are custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary sinners, foolish Atheists; desirous of change, and seditious; for their destruction comes sodainly, &amp; who knows the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> And that we may never <hi>know</hi> it, the Lord by his <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> work in us the true <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:204961:61"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>